Hello everyone. Thank you so much for
being here. We're going to start the
afternoon session at 1:45. Um, thank you
so much for being the hot weather. I
hope you guys enjoy lunch. We understand
that there might be a long line waiting
for lunch. We really appreciate you guys
for being so forgiving, so patient with
us. Really appreciate it. The afternoon
session is going to be amazing show. So,
uh, enjoy. Thank you so much.
and welcome.
We are going to start off our next
session. Uh my name is Maxwell Zeff. I'm
a writer with Wired and I'll be
introducing some of our panelists today.
But to start, everyone's going to give
short keynote talk. Uh the first is none
other than Don Song. uh she's a
professor at UC Berkeley, the
co-director of Berkeley RDI, and most
recently a VP of AI research at Meta
Super Intelligence Labs. So, everyone
please give a round of applause for
Dawn.
[applause]
>> Thank you.
>> Hi everyone. I hope everyone has enjoyed
the morning session and I'm going to
kick off the afternoon session. Thanks
everyone for being here. Uh today I will
talk about towards building safe and
secure agentic AI.
So uh year 2025 was uh termed the year
of agents and this year we continue to
see further explosive growth of agents
and uh on one hand we want to continue
to enjoy the great benefits brought by
this frontier AI capabilities uh and
agent AI. On the other hand, we also
need to pay attention to a broad
spectrum of different types of AI risks.
And also in particular, I want to stress
that as we deploy AI in the real world,
it's important to consider the presence
of attackers for a number of reasons.
First, history has shown that attackers
always follow the footsteps of new
technology developments or sometimes
even leaders. And also this time the
stake is even higher with AI. As AI
controls more and more systems,
attackers will have higher and higher
incentives to compromise them. And also
as AI becomes more and more capable, the
consequence of misuse by attackers will
also become more and more severe. And
hence it's really important to consider
agentic AI in the adversarial setting.
And in particular, the overall goal we
are trying to achieve here is to advance
safe and secure AI innovation to ensure
its potential benefits are responsibly
realized and widely shared. In order to
uh to achieve this goal, we need to
develop uh different types of technical
uh and also social technical solutions
to build safe and secure agentic AI. And
in particular this is a large domain and
we need to uh actually uh decoup uh
divide the problems into different uh
categories. So the first part I will
talk about is on building secure agentic
AI uh to protect our agentic AI systems
from malicious attacks from attackers.
And second, I will uh talk about how we
can then on the other side mitigate
misuse. In particular, as AI agentic AI
capabilities continue to increase, we
need to be able to mit mitigate misuse
by attackers. And in particular, I will
focus on the impact of frontier AI in
the landscape of cyber security.
So first, let's talk about building
secure agentic AI. Aenti systems they
can be very powerful and very dynamic.
These systems they use for example large
language models for reasoning planning
and uh figuring out actions what actions
to take use different tools and so on
and then they uh allow agents to
interact with the environments to
perceive from the environment and also
take actions in the environments.
And when we talk about safety and
security of aentic AI systems, this
actually is much more complex when in
the past we only talked about AI safety
and security of at the model level
itself. At the model level, you give it
the inputs, a prompt, [snorts]
you get outputs. But with the Aentti
systems, the agents can take rich
actions, can have a lot of privileges,
and the consequences um of attack and
misbehaviors can be much more severe.
Uh so to learn more information about AI
safety and security at the model level,
uh I uh encourage you to watch my uh I
clear keynote last year. But given
interest of time for the rest of this
talk I will focus on uh safety and
security issues of agent AI at the
overall aenti system level.
When we talk about agent AI we are not
talking about just one single type of
agents. Actually there is a broad design
space. In our recent paper overviewing
the attack and defense landscape of
Aentic AI uh systems, we also outline
the overall design space of Aentic AI
along um multiple dimensions as listed
here. And the point I want to emphasize
here is that along each dimension as we
increase the agent flexibility along
each of the dimensions including the
input trust level the the two use
workflow uh and so on uh for the agents.
We are also simultaneously increasing
the attack surface. And overall again in
our overview paper overviewing the the
whole landscape of attack and defense uh
space for agentic AI we also uh identify
diverse attack factors and the different
types of security risks uh in the
agentic AI space and you can check out
paper for more details and this also is
not just theoretical in fact as together
with the rise of agentic AI we are also
seeing real world attacks on agents
that's rising fast. For example, uh claw
hub uh for uh open claw uh already had a
significant fraction of his skills that
are actually malicious skills and we see
uh actually a number of um real world
incidents on attacks on agents and it's
rising fast
and hence
uh what I want to emphasize here is that
as we increase in aging capability
autonomy and the set privileges agents
have. We it's absolutely critical that
we need to um have stronger security
guarantees and uh and to ensure a set of
uh different types of security goals
including confidentiality, integrity,
availability and also agentic contextual
security and privacy to ensure that
agents actions are aligned with users
intent.
In order to achieve this, we need to
develop new solutions for building
secure agentic AI systems. And here I
will talk about two uh technologies for
two uh stages, two main stages of the
agent AI system development life cycle.
The first one is on evaluation and risk
assessments and the second one is on
defenses. So in order to build a secure
aentic AI systems, we first need to be
able to do rigorous evaluation and risk
assessments so that we can actually
understand the different types of risks
and different uh potential uh attacks on
uh any given agent systems. So my group
and with collaborators we have had long
journeys uh in uh in this direction. uh
and we have been among the earliest to
develop for example the first comp
comprehensive evaluation framework for
the trustworthiness of large rank models
for multimodel uh models for video
models and also for overall agentic
systems and many of these papers have uh
won best paper awards and and so on and
uh here also is a overview of how we
actually think about the uh overall
design space of automatic right teaming
for aentic AI.
For automatic right teaming for aentic
AI essentially we can think about the
system as an optimization loop for
automatic attack generation where we
have uh we can have these generators uh
that uses uh different uh algorithms uh
including um uh machine models and so on
to automatically generate attack
candidates. And then these attack
candidates are then launched in the
environments where the agent is
interacting and then uh getting feedback
and then the feedback can be used then
further to update uh these um uh uh to
update essentially the generator for
these attack candidates. And this can be
essentially an automatic feedback loop
uh using different methods to um to
optimize to uh generates more effective
uh uh attack ci candidates. So the
different algorithms for this auto
automatic optimization loop can include
for example search based um and also uh
for example evolution algorithm genetic
algorithms and also gradient based and
also for example reinforcement learning
based and so on and also this overall um
agent uh automatic righting framework
can be agentic itself. So essentially we
can build this automatic reting agents
to actually do automatic reting on a
target uh agent AI system. And this is
just a a quick uh overview of the
different types of uh automatic writing
agents uh and also um prematures that we
have built uh using the different
algorithms I just mentioned for agentic
AI and also recently uh together with
other collaborators we have developed
this um unifi platform for agent writing
called decoding trust uh for agents uh
platform which has a large number of
simulating environments allows agents to
act the K agents to run in the
simulating environments and using this
automated uh automated right teaming
agents that I mentioned to automatically
then generate attack candidates and
continue to optimize it and and so on as
well.
And with that I also want to um want to
mention our most recent work called the
super red. The goal of super red is
actually about developing an open
ecosystem for this type of automatic
right teaming so that we can bring the
community together to build the best
automatic right teaming uh framework and
system. So then we can overall together
help improve the resilience of aentic
systems. So the uh super red is designed
as a open source framework that you can
run uh that's modularized. So you can
bring in uh different attack algorithms.
You can bring in different evaluation
benchmarks and plug in different types
of agents environments and so on. So
everything's modular modularized. So and
also with uh also fine grain controlled
modularized thread model as well. And
superite allows you to run any attacker
against any systems with any threat
model. And uh you can find out more
information on the super website. And
currently it already comes in with 35
modules uh to run um today. And uh as
the community contributes and plug in
new attack algorithms, new evaluation
benchmarks and new environments, this
will uh build the flywheel to have the
uh community together to build um this
really powerful uh uh open ecosystem for
uh automated writing. So we welcome
everyone to check it out and contribute.
And with the system you also get um
detailed uh runtime uh for example
uh obser uh observability transparent
insights and dashboards and uh and so on
and it's really easy to install. So
really encourage uh the audience to go
check it out. Uh so that's on
evaluation. Another important uh part of
course is on actually building the AI
defense itself and given the complexity
of the issue of there's no single silver
bullets for building effective defense
uh in instead we need to uh deploy
defense in depth and also uh deploy and
adopt best practice uh for security such
as this privilege privilege separation
and see by design and secure by design
to ensure that we in the end hopefully
we and actually uh get um properly
secure systems.
And again in our overview paper, we
actually list out um close to 20
different types of defense mechanisms
that you can use to uh build as a layer
of defense. Uh and also here's one
example of our recent work called Proent
uh which is the first um [clears throat]
programmable privilege control and guard
rail for um agents with contextual
security where we allow um the uh the
guard rail to also automatically
generate dynamic security policies to
dynamically reduce uh the agents
privilege to achieve this privilege uh
with the contextual uh security.
So with that that's the first part
building secure agent AI to protect the
agent AI systems from malicious attacks.
Now let me quickly uh talk about the
second part which is how we can actually
mitigate misuse and in particular in the
um space of uh cyber security.
So again as I mentioned that there's a
broad spectrum of different types of AI
risks but for me personally I do
strongly believe that cyber security is
one of the biggest AI risk domains and
this is also why uh my group will have
been among the earliest to actually
working uh to investigate the impact of
frontier AI in the landscape of cyber
security and also with uh our work
demonstrating the uh increased uh risk
in the space. So the key question here
is how will front AI change the
landscape of cyber security especially
given that uh AI as a dual use
technology can help both attacker sides
and defender sides. And in order to
answer this question we need to actually
do detailed analysis through the complex
uh kill chain u for different stages of
separate attacks and also for defenses.
And in order to achieve this, my group
with our collaborators, we have
developed a leading uh benchmarks that
has been used by essentially all
frontier labs on evaluating frontier
capabilities in cyber security that
actually uh covers covers across the
vulnerability life cycle uh including
vulnerability discovery, validation,
doing exploit generation and also
patching.
And with our work separate gym uh which
is a a a benchmark containing large
scale widely distributed open source
software uh we showed that uh frontier
AI is capability in cyber security is
increasing drastically um and and also
right within recent cloud mythos and
project glasswing also further
demonstrated the capabilities of
frontier AI uh capability in cyber And
also with the recent exploit gym um also
showing that the frontier AI now can
also automatically generate exploits and
these exploits can even bypass existing
uh standard security mechanisms and also
as the um many of you may have heard
about the recent incidents from opening
eye hugging face. Uh the agent actually
while trying to solve the um exploit gym
benchmark our benchmark uh it actually
broke out of the um uh the isolation
sandbox from open uh environment and
then actually in the end did very
sophisticated attacks to actually in the
end uh was able to break into a hacking
phase uh infrastructure as well. So all
this illustrates that um now with the
increased AI frontier AI capabilities
the agents now have really strong
capabilities in cyber. The agents this
was not even a misuse. It was not a
malicious uh you know attacker trying to
use agents to compromise another system.
The agents actually did this on its own.
So first of all this told us that now
with the agents capabilities even the
evaluation infrastructure itself can now
be are now becoming part of the attack
surface and also this really uh is a
wakeup call showing the power and the
potential risk these um agent capability
can can bring uh to the world
um in order to address all these issues.
So first we have launched um a frontier
AI cyber security observatory uh bring
the community together to do continuous
monitoring of the uh frontier
capabilities increase in cyber security
and also a bigger question is what can
we do especially given that uh AI as a
do use technology it can help both
attacker side and defender side and also
the challenge here is that coding
capabilities and cyber capabilities are
two sides of the same coin. And what's
even worse is that we call this
equivalence class problem is that the
same capabilities that can help
defenders essentially in our paper we
show that they can also be used by
attackers in the corresponding stage for
attacks.
And furthermore, there's natural
symmetry between defense and offense.
And uh for example, attackers only need
to find one successful vulnerability and
exploit and do a successful attack where
uh to succeed where defenders need to
defend against all attacks. And also in
our paper we also show uh
a number of other natural symmetries
between attackers and defenders uh
showing that unfortunately due to this
natural symmetry in the near term AI is
going to help attackers more than
defenders. So the question is what can
we do to shift AI to help defenders more
than attackers
in uh throughout the history of uh cyber
security community and also including um
my own work uh in the last you know two
to three decades. We have gone through
three different paradigms for building
defenses. The first one is reactive
defense where defenders develop
uh attack detection and blocking
mechanisms
um and also other uh mitigation
mechanisms after attack has happened.
Unfortunately with this defense paradigm
um my belief that and al our analysis
shows that attackers can still benefit
more from AI than defenders.
And the second paradigm is proactive
defense through bug finding where in
this case the defenders can use AI to
try to find bugs in code first and then
hope to fix them before attackers.
However, in this case again uh attacker
also can be at an advantage uh in the
sense attackers only need to find one
successful uh attack. So we really hope
that with the AI it can help uh help us
to achieve the third paradigm uh in a
more uh effective way which is proactive
defense through security by
construction.
Using this approach
uh we develop we architect and build
provably secure programs and systems in
contrast to bug finding and attack
defense and reactive uh defense um uh
attack detection and reactive defense
mechanisms. And so through uh program
verification uh using formal
verification we hope that we can
actually build systems with probably
secure guarantees that can completely
eliminate entire like classes of uh
vulnerabilities and so on.
So this ultimately will put defenders uh
in an advantage to attackers and in fact
we have already enters the era of
formally verified systems with many uh
formally verified uh systems uh
including micro kernels uh opinion uh uh
compilers and and so on. Well, however,
it's been labor intensive to actually uh
prove uh do the proof engineering for
the systems and hence they have not been
widely used and my group has been among
the earliest also with our collaborators
to uh uh to develop different methods
for theorem proving and I strongly
believe that now we are reaching
inflection points using frontier AI. We
can uh further enhance formal
mathematical reasoning and automate
theorem proving. We hope that using this
approach instead of just generating code
we can actually generate a proofy uh
secure code where we um combine the
program uh generation uh program
synthesis with program verification
and towards this goal we also have
developed uh the current leading
benchmarks for verifiable code
generation including Verina and Varo
which now uh provides
uh allows us to evaluate AI capabilities
for verifying uh uh for verifying codes
uh at the um at a large scale repository
level and we hope that with the
community to uh together we can make uh
rapid progress in this uh space and we
can um now finally use AI to help shift
the dynamics to help AI help defenders
more than uh attackers. So with that I
want to conclude uh my talk and I want
to just briefly want to mention that uh
besides this work we also are developing
various work on open ecosystem for agent
evaluation including agents last exam uh
a benchmark for evaluating uh agents uh
capabilities in real world economically
valuable uh long horizon uh tasks uh
over 55 different uh sectors and also uh
agent beats for building a new standards
for open standardized reproducible agent
evaluation and u uh you can learn more
uh at later today's workshop on future
of aging evaluation with that thanks
everyone All
right.
Can we give another round of applause
for Don? That was great. Uh, next up
we're going to have another speaker. We
have Oriel Vignyals, VP of research at
Google DeepMine and Gemini tech lead.
So, Oral, why don't you come on up? Give
a round of applause for Oral.
Hi everyone. It's great to be back in my
alma mater at Berkeley. Um, today I know
this is about agents, but I've been
focused a lot more lately on recursive
self-improvement. So, I'll try to give
you a little bit of my own perspective
on it. Um, let's see if the slides come
up. That's not my slide at least. Always
interesting.
Um
okay anyways so I'll start talking but
the slides hopefully come up. Um but I
think one of the things that uh at
DeepMind we work for a very long time is
agents actually and it's kind of
interesting to see the evolution of what
agents have meant to be over the years
especially when you have a company that
has been building around reinforcement
learning which defines what an agent is.
uh for over a decade now. Um so my first
slide if it appears would show the usual
traditional reinforcement learn learning
loop where you have an agent and you
have an environment and there's
observations and actions being
interchanged and generally those are
like the agent is powered by a neuronet
and so on. Uh but then um the the
observations and actions are generally
fixed and the environment at the time
and it makes sense that's there's my
slides. Um the environment at the time
we use video games which hopefully makes
a lot of sense today. The arguments we
were making at the time people were like
saying hey games are not real world. I
mean this is not perhaps going to be as
impactful the technology as as um you
know as as you make it make us believe.
Obviously, hindsight tells us this
technology has been and is going to be
very impactful. But video games have
this very nice property of being
sandboxed even more properly than the
current sandboxes we have. Uh so we were
testing algorithms and idea on the agent
capabilities on go you know Starcraft
and all sorts of different games until
of course games were like we ran out of
games that we had tackled the most
complex games and so on. I'll get back
to that point a bit later about games.
Um, but you know the prelim era agents
the graph was fairly simple. Uh, if you
look now at what agents mean and we've
heard so many times in the talks in the
morning and now like that I don't want
to go too deep into this but there's a
bit of a reshuffle. I think the one
that's most profound is that the
environment is hard to disentangle from
the agent. So I put the environment
inside of the agent, right? The
environment is like a machine possibly
with access to network, internet and so
on in which the agent harness that has a
lang large language model as a brain.
Not that different from that other
picture that was at the time powered by
a neural network trained specifically
for like a game or a domain. But this
sort of interaction is so important and
so critical that it's very hard to
disentangle. And then unlike before, we
have a user that is interacting with
this agent, you know, perhaps coding or
asking it hard questions that might take
a while to to run. And the environment
in general can be shared with the user.
It might be that's my machine. There's
also some machines that can virtual
machines that can spawn on the cloud and
cloud and so on so forth. So
I'm I'm going to describe a bit what I
think you know a very practical
definition of self-improvement and
recursive self-improvement is through
this lens. I think it's not that
different actually what that's why I'm
I'm bringing it up uh in the agents
section uh what SI and RSI are. So
self-improvement
is kind of a bit of a nuance over what
agents are doing for us today. I would
say probably the user is not as
interactive with the system. I mean
self-improvement means that the system
is operating by itself mostly without
much input. So a user might give us a
specification and then this process
might run for hours and hours um uh or
days and days rather than maybe being
more interactive and then critically
there's a fitness function or whatever
the improvement target is or might be. I
think in the morning there was a tetric
right as the as the target or or the
fitness that then the system was trying
to optimize but it's not that different
from an agent is kind of almost a detail
and then if you go one step further the
recursivity the simplest way to think
about it is like well wait a second um
the agent harness itself the code that
runs the agent and even the brains
behind the agent actions the LLM or set
of LLMs
now can also be modified, right? So
these are trivially can be seen as part
of the environment, right? The code that
runs your harness and the model maybe
it's an object that you can sort of
upload uh you know to to your server
that's serving tokens and so on. Um and
so recursive the recursive part is just
allowing this environment and agent
harness to modify itself or the model
and it's useful to distinguish
self-improvement in the harness space.
Right? This this is more like the code
the how you do like compaction all sorts
of different things that um you need to
implement for agents um you know what
tools does it have available and so on
and then of course al also the model
weights themselves right which could be
rewritten from scratch could be
fine-tuned and I mean the action space
for um the recursivity part is anything
that modifies that object right so this
is fairly simple um I don't think we've
seen very impactful
actual recursive self-improvement
examples yet. Certainly many
self-improvement examples. Um those are
more commonly seen but of course this is
coming and it has fairly deep
consequences into how we do our own
research to develop then the harness and
the LLMs which of course is at the core
of what we at many frontier labs are
doing. So unpacking a bit what are you
know how would you expect this agent
with the brain to do recursive
self-improvement it's quite useful to
put a bit of my researcher hat I mean we
all or maybe not but many of us have
written papers have thought about ideas
um to change the field and so on so the
process in which you would expect a
fully capable recursive self-improvement
system to do is not that different from
the process that you know many of us
have been playing you know as a game for
years to publish papers and trying to
get our techniques adopted widely right
so this can be decomposed in so many
different ways but I think it's useful
to think about it in these four ways um
more detail can be you can zoom in on
one of these and so on maybe that's a
good point for discussion but very
critically there's an ideation phase
where you take all the previous work um
all that you know about the field and
you select which ideas are worth
pursuing fundamentally, right? So this
is a kind of a very important reasoning
step which makes you go into a next
stage of then implementing set idea,
right? Like you have to implement it. It
might be complex, it might be simple. Uh
after which you maybe have an
experimentation phase, you run the code,
there's bugs, it doesn't work, maybe you
insist, maybe you you give up and go
back to another idea and so on so forth.
And last but not least, you evaluate
what happened and whether the hypothesis
maybe that you form on the ideation
phase is verified or not. And then you
might obviously traditionally write a
paper in a recursive self-improvement
system. You might just go back and loop
loop around right. So what's critical
about this and my observation is
currently a lot of effort is done in the
middle two boxes implementation. I mean
we know how powerful uh coding agents
are these days. So I think there's
certainly a lot of progress and
enthusiasm behind implementation
uh and experimentation as well like
running compiling you know debugging
also I think we've seen perhaps because
it's the most interactive with the user
um so more more similar to
self-improvement rather than recursive
self-improvement we've seen a lot a lot
of progress uh there as well but the
other two not so much so I'm going to
zoom in a little bit on to kind of some
maybe thoughtprovoking thoughts on what
might happen and what needs to happen
for us to really achieve this loop
meaningfully with full automation.
So evaluation is always a very important
topic. I find as a community evaluation
and data have never been um perhaps
highlighted as much as they should have.
Um even you know different papers that
propose a new data set might have been
regarded as an application and not
worthy of publication in one of the
bigger conferences certainly years ago.
So I want to insist on evaluation
because it's so critical. So how do we
measure progress in a more like
scientific way as we are developing
better models and better harnesses,
right? The first way is kind of the
obvious way. We take some capabilities
we believe are important um in this and
some benchmarks. So SWE pro MLB bench
perhaps per perplexity on held out data
in pre-training is commonly what most
people are are optimizing for these
days. And then you just heel climb,
right? You just say, "Look, we're going
to get better at all this." And
hopefully by doing this, recursive
self-improvement might emerge. And
certainly there are pros for this
approach. I mean, this is exactly how
we've been training LLMs for a few years
now. Evaluation is reasonably cheap. We
know how to do it. It's well defined.
But I mean the cons I would say that the
the one that is the worst is that it's
very indirect measurement of actually a
system that might truly develop
recursive self-improvement and of course
there's all sorts of issues with
overfeitting cheating um and also the
current evals at least that we have are
focusing as I said mostly on those two
middle boxes implementation and
experimentation.
Now a much better way would be to
evaluate literally for what we care to
improve the capability of which is in
this case recursive self-improvement.
There are some benchmarks that are
appearing because of course this is
getting gaining traction in the field.
Um post train bench is one example but
Don was telling me about another one. So
we're going to see this popping over the
next few weeks and months for sure. And
of course the advantage is that we
measure what we care for, right? So we
are improving the self-improvement
capability. If we set the evaluation in
a way that is like hey like is the inner
loop itself is like hey evaluate some
other metric go for a few tries and see
how much improvement you get. Right?
That's your evaluation. It's a bit meta
but it's it's more powerful. Of course
there's a few cons. This is expensive
right now to evaluate. You literally
need to run an agent for a while to
improve some set metric. And then the
inner loop still will be you know I
guess improving tetries or some
something that is not perhaps the actual
metric that in production we'll care to
evaluate which would be hey I want to
automate my whole frontier lab um create
the best model in the world right and I
mean these evaluations might be a bit
out of distribution um as they stand
today
and then perhaps a modification of these
very relevant for what's been you know
the discussion of the day and certainly
um what I expect to increasingly happen
in the field is to tweak the previous
one by also not only evaluating for hey
how much can I you know better play
tetries over um you know three hours of
compute that I give this agent but also
how do I achieve that improvement right
uh I don't want to see cheating I don't
want I want to see creativity I want to
see certain aspects of intelligence um
and evaluate them with you know some
powerful reward models that are a bit
more fasily evaluated but still very
important capabilities that we expect
this model to to exhibit. Um so an
example just to give it a concrete and
maybe to use ideiation as I think a
fairly underexplored area in general in
LLM training. So well how do we evaluate
ideas right? Um well there's many
aspects if you are a reviewer in a
conference right you're looking for
research taste novelty you know
efficiency elegancy is this going to
stand the test of time this kind of
technique and so on so forth right so
you can imagine trying to evaluate the
behavior of an agent doing recursive
self-improvement on that ideation stage
based on a few of these that we can
write rules and try to automate a little
bit but it's very hard at the moment And
these are very underststudied. So I
think this is going to take us some time
to figure out to advance these
capabilities and the reasoning the
automatic reasoning that might be
required for us to be able to optimize
with you know reinforcement learning on
top of this system and I would argue
even as humans are not that good. I mean
we have very expensive systems
conferences review processes and so on
and transformers actually took many
years to become mainstream. um
distillation which is getting more
famous now was actually rejected um from
the conference we submitted at and it
took many years and some sort of random
process for it to reemerge as hey this
might be actually useful and I mean all
of you probably have your own sour
rejected paper story of a great idea
that in hindsight you you should have
been accepted by this automated and
expensive process that we set up. So
automating this truly in an agentic way
might take some effort and and but it's
worth pursuing to achieve RSI. Uh of
course we've seen and I bring back the
games here. This is not a surprise that
our agents are sort of doing things a
little bit differently than what we
expect. So we had um very famous games
that are exploited in some different
ways. The other video doesn't work but
it's uh also quite funny. Um so this is
many years that we've seen this coming.
And then to wrap up, right, we need to
obviously it's an incredible time to be
to be alive, right? It's it's it's
definitely clear that RSI will increase
perhaps 10x or more the speed of
progress of certain engineering and
science task for sure. Uh but you know
be mindful of how we set the goals,
misalignment, resource reallocation, uh
how the labs are run might change. So we
need to be quite careful about how how
to take different steps in this. And as
I was arguing, it might not come as fast
as we thought it would because first
evaluation is very hard and ideation is
also very hard. So these are two
important components. Um also some
process might be just limited by
physical constraints. I mean the chips
cannot go faster than what they're
designed to be. Uh of course also like
speed of light and so on, right? To
transmit data around like the chip and
so on has also certain limitations. And
then last but not least, performance
that we had obtained as humans might be
clo close to an asymto. So by adding
recursive self-improvement, we might
anyways not see a drastic improvement.
Right? So how good is alpha go with
respect to the you know perfect go game
and unclear. Uh or another example is
sometimes it's kind of annoying how well
these models write and you have to make
it look a little bit worse. So they got
too good at writing for example, right?
So there's some of these uh domains
certainly where better doesn't mean
better um necessarily and with these
thoughtprovoking thoughts hopefully um
we can have a good panel later but
looking forward to the rest of the
session. Thank you very much. Thanks.
All right. Thank you, Oriel. So next up
we're gonna have a talk from Voych
Zeremba who's a co-founder of OpenAI and
he recently has started working as a
head of AI resilience at the OpenAI
foundation. So everyone give it up for
Voych.
Okay,
wonderful. Thank you guys for having me
here. Okay, slides.
Okay,
would be nice if that would work. Okay,
next slide.
Okay, slide before.
Okay,
great. Wonderful. [sighs]
Uh that's an evidence that AGI is not
yet here.
Um so as it was mentioned I'm part of
OpenAI Foundation. This is like a
interesting entity. OpenAI went
restructured number of months ago and
now there is a nonprofit that owns
around one quarter of OpenAI equity. So
that's like a massive amount of
resources and one of the divisions of
OpenAI Foundation is AI resilience. I'm
going to explain today what AI
resilience is and it's similar to AI
safety and yet it's different.
Okay, please
next slide. Okay,
I need the help from the sky. So um the
today I will explain what AI resilience
is and I found it to be uh the most
useful to explain it through analogy to
fire resilience and uh then uh we'll go
into um what does it mean for AI playing
out well. So the way how the
presentation will go will be uh at first
describing similarities between fire and
AI and obviously fire is very different
than AI in many many ways. So uh these I
are by no means uh perfect. Um so both
fire and AI are general purpose
technologies. It means that they have
really broad applicability.
uh in case of fire it was used or it is
used to heat food, provide the warmth to
people, smelter metal, it's part of
engines. It's pretty much fundamental to
our civilization. Uh something similar
is happening with AI. Uh AI is now part
of the um knowledge and uh wisdom
development, part of the scientific
process. And also if you if you take
seriously where robotics is going, it
will be just the uh fundamental part of
the economic engine of the future. So
both AI and fire are general purpose
technologies. Okay, that's one
similarity.
Another similarity is both technologies
come with risks. So in case of fire,
there was like a number of major uh
fires in the past. London was burned
four times. Boston, Chicago, uh like a
80% of London was consumed during the
large fires. H now today we pretty well
understand the risks coming from uh
fire. Um that's less true about AI. When
you ask people about the risks of AI,
it's kind of like a people point in
different directions. Um there are like
a many things pointed out. It's just
enough to open newspaper and hear what
people are scared about. And I would say
um these risks are highly uncertain. It
actually might turn out that some of
these risks will end up uh being a
paperwork and some of them will turn out
to be 10x more than what people expected
and some of the risks might not even be
at the least. Okay. So fire and AI they
come with risks. Okay. Here is like an
interesting twist in the story. So it
turned out turns out that in case of
fire the way how people try to um
provide the safety for for fire was uh
through restriction. So curfew comes
from French and it means extinguish
fire. In the medieval time it was common
that if you had fire going on at your
home during the night, police would come
and knock at your door and ask it to
extinguish fire. So obviously that had a
you know that that's like a decrease of
capabilities of the fire and it also
turned out that at least in this
particular case actually it didn't work
out well. The great fire of London
happened despite of curfews. So the uh
method of restricting uh uh fire didn't
actually work out for this particular
technology. Now in case of AI
restrictions um this is like a more
complicated there are some restrictions
that actually seem to be working pretty
well. An example uh would be um most of
the platforms they uh follow
non-conensual intimate uh images
restriction they don't allow for this uh
now some people advocated for open
source uh uh restrictions and these are
not uh really uh implemented. So um I
would say that in case of AI the
restrictions didn't work out well. So
now you might ask um what uh what
actually what did it take for a fire to
become um uh safe and it turns out that
there wasn't silver bullet. It's not
that there is a single solution to uh
make fire safe and it ends up being
multi-layer ecosystem approach. So you
have these um uh systems for early
detection of a fire. There are also
people who are trained uh toward dealing
with firefighter brigades. They have a
special vehicles. There are fire trucks.
They have a specially designed hoses. Um
now um there is also the it turns out
that the cities they have a supply of
water uh spread throughout the city with
fire hydrants at the sufficient pressure
and the quantity necessary in order to
extinguish fire. There are also
materials which are specially designed.
So there's like a we switch from wood to
uh metal and concrete. There are also
inspections, insurance and u also um
let's say um designated areas for exit
uh and so on and so forth. So once we
implemented this um actually uh now fire
is not something that we are
particularly worried about. So we are in
the place that the um none of us is
worried about this particular uh um uh
risks we we are able to really fully
harness the benefits.
So you might ask actually did it even uh
work and the claim is it actually worked
remarkably well. So these days we have
uh cities which are order of magnitude
denser than the medieval cities. we have
many more sources of fire. So there's
like a let's say um electricity, gas,
industry and even data centers these
days. And fire is not something that
people are worried about.
So now you might ask okay what would it
be analogous for the AI itself and I
find that people in AI space they try to
think about the silver bullet that there
would be one solution in order for AI to
play out well and I actually think that
that's a incorrect way of thinking about
it. I also think that it's not just
enough to make a individual models
aligned though that's like a part of the
uh solution uh the the there needs to be
number of solutions in the ecosystem. So
what I mean by that uh let me give you
some examples. Um in case of the uh like
a models become for instance quite
capable when it comes to biological
domain and uh many people foresee the
risks coming uh from uh models uh making
it easy to uh manufacture uh uh
pandemics. Now if we think that that's
the risk then dealing with these risks
uh requires and and if we also assume
that there will be diffusion of advanced
open source models then it might not be
sufficient to guard rail these
capabilities within the frontier labs.
That's like a one of the things that
should be done but that won't be enough.
We might need to harden the environment
itself. So for instance in that space uh
people are uh thinking about ideas like
uh sanitizing air because if air is
sanitized uh then actually uh pathogens
wouldn't be able to spread. Maybe in
case of cyber security we need to get to
the point that the software is formally
verified. Uh that would uh prevent it
from being hacked by super intelligence.
Maybe in case of safety accidents we
need the public data database similar to
how it's happening in case of aviation
that the uh incidents are being publicly
reported and the ones who reported uh uh
gained by reporting uh uh uh safe harbor
uh and so on and so forth. So um now
creation of this uh might uh uh some of
them could be achieved through creation
of the companies working on these
efforts. Some of them might be uh
achieved through the creation of the
nonprofits. But like a fundamentally we
are in the place that uh it would be
important for a number of capable people
for people who are like a reality
warping for uh people's co like figures
to ask themselves what needs to be built
in the world for the AI to play out well
and then to go after building the new
institutions and organizations and in
case of open AI foundation we have tons
of resources to support endeavors like
that And whether or not AI resilience
will succeed depends on people in this
room. Thank you guys very much.
>> All right. Thank you, Voych. Very
fascinating. Uh next up we have Jerry
Tore who is going to speak with us. He
is a former VP of AI research at OpenAI
and now is the CEO and co-founder of
Core Automation, one of the most
interesting new AI labs startups. So,
give it up for Jerry.
Thank you very much for inviting me.
Very happy to be here.
uh long horizon agents are clearly one
of the frontiers of AI research right
now. If I look at my codec session, my
median is usage is around 10 minutes. If
I look at the mean, it's around 20. Why
is it not more? Why agents are not
working for me for longer time? I think
it's a very worthwhile question to be
asking today for AI researchers. But to
to start with, let's start with the
obvious, which is we already live in the
era of agents. Agents are here, but we
are very early in this era. H in my mind
03 was the first really agentic model
and that model was on really released in
April last year. So we are just just
barely more than a year in the era of
agents. That means the models are very
early. They have improved vastly since
03. But at the same time there's much
more improvements to be had. The
products are improving. The adoption is
coming. A lot of things are still not
figured out. And we live in those
beautiful times and that beautiful
opportunity to to figure those things
out for the for for the future decades
of agent proliferation.
What's even thinking about the
definition what makes agent an agent? I
think I think agent is a very fuzzy term
that is hard to fully define what it is
for me like I I put some pieces that I
think make an agent which is agents use
tools because agents should be able to
act on my behalf. Agents are most likely
async. I tell agent something to do and
it goes on and does its work. Agents are
usually goal oriented which you specify
something high level what you want the
agent to do and the agent fills in the
blanks and agents are working usually
over long horizons of time. You don't do
back and forth uh every every five
minutes you let agent do its work for
extended extended periods of time. And
whenever we extend the length of the
time that the agents are working, there
is this pretty obvious observation that
every step the neural networks that we
train are probabilistic. They make
failures. So with every step there is
that there is an exponentially growing
through the length of your trajectory
chance that something something goes
wrong. H that was a very big reason why
we couldn't have agents for for for many
years until until very recently because
because the neural networks were getting
off the rails and this is um pretty like
classical assumption from the
reinforcement learning literature and
why do we need actually reinforcement
learning and the moment happened when
when when me and my team were able to
scale reinforcement learning to larger
and larger or um amounts of compute
where we finally found a recipe that
allowed us to train models to recover
from their own mistakes, train on their
own trajectories and that suddenly
started making the models be able to
succeed and harder and harder harder
task. And what what did we see? The
first thing is obvious like the more
compute you spend like you could see
proportionally on a on an algorithmic
plot the capabilities of them all
improving. We have also seen the other
thing which um is one of the most like
important shifts in mind in machine
learning of the of the recent years
which is the more the model thinks the
more tokens it spends on a task
performance improves. So not only the
models strength of reinforcement
learning were not falling on the trap of
exponentially increasing the chance of
failure on a trajectory. They were able
to recover from that but but they were
able to even even keep productively
thinking for longer and longer. So
essentially the longer your trajectory
the better the results you are getting.
We we we enter the test time compute era
and token maxing. So
uh then then we we we have this now this
is a plot a lot of people thinking about
agents are very familiar. It's a plot
for how long agents can work from us.
And since we started uh scaling
reinforcement learning, it reaches new
and new heights with the latest readouts
of around 12 hours, 16 hours for for
some of the best frontier models of the
of the day today. So the question is
maybe maybe this is it. Maybe we have
reinforcement learning. It works. We can
throw a lot of money at it and maybe
maybe we just keep scaling and we'll
have agents working for for whatever
amount of time we would like. Is that is
that the case? Is that the solution?
Unfortunately, there are there are
problems. There are there are
challenges. I don't think I don't think
we are we are done yet. The first
problem which is that the the economics
is here kind of unfavorable [snorts] in
many ways to sample a trajectory of
length n you generally your cost is
proportional to the length of
trajectory. with a quadratic attention
is even even slightly bigger. But let's
think for a second linearly that the
cost of each token is fixed. So to
sample a trajectory of n tokens is
proportional to the length of it. But
also how are today's reinforcement
learning algorithms work? they assign
single reward for that trajectory which
is there aren't really any in modern RL
credit assignment methods to assign that
reward to any specific tokens which
means you you get one reward to the
trajectory of of of n tokens which the
information per token you are getting is
roughly one divided by n and the cost of
that trajectory is is also n which means
that your learning signal decays
quadratically in the length of your of
your trajectory on the horizon you are
you are you are doing which is if if if
it would be if it would be linear it
would be like pretty okay to keep
throwing more money and we know if we
want to train agents to work twice as
hard for twice longer time we need to
spend twice more money that's a pretty
reasonable thing but if it's quadratic
it is becoming pretty brutal the big
labs today are very good at spending a
lot of money training models but the
quadratic cost makes the makes makes the
scaling of that considerably harder than
it would than it would seem at first
sight. Um the second bit which is even
harder is latency because as much as
there's more and more investment coming
to the AI world nowadays, no one has
time. There's there isn't that much time
and the the latency problem comes from
the following. Imagine you have to
sample a 12-hour trajectory of an agent.
It takes 12 hours to to sample it. And
then you take a gradient step to update
your model to reinforce the successful
trajectories. And then then then you
have updated weights. And then you can
you do you sample another 12hour
trajectory. You you were able to do full
two gradient steps in a day of your of
your reinforcement learning agent. That
means roughly 14 gradient steps a week.
That means like 60 gradient steps a
month. It doesn't it is not a very fast
training method. And no one no one has
time in in in in today's world. So
training for very long trajectories and
for long horizon thinking is
meaningfully very very hard harder than
that than than many realize. And a lot
of the progress in the field and the
reason we have even any agents that can
think for a long time is usually we put
some kind of harness on top of it
because if the agents are very good at
doing short horizon things, short
horizon tasks and the truth is a lot of
long horizon work can be glued very
successfully together from doing smaller
and smaller things. And we have this
things called slashgoal in in in in
codeex in cloud code which is very
powerful. We just create a fixed goal
for our model. It runs for however long
long it can. Then it revisits itself and
it continues to do that. We have we have
plan mode. We have we have many ways we
can we have sub agents. There are
various ways that are not native to them
all. They are not back propagated
through they are not trained but but to
utilize the models ability to work on
shorter term goals and structure from
them being able to spend more and more.
you you're very successful. But the
history of machine learning has always
been that whatever we can back propagate
through wins with things that we that we
that we cannot.
Um everyone everyone's probably pretty
uh familiar with auto research and what
auto research means and
the story of almost every auto research
rollout is you get a lot of progress
pretty early but this if you go further
and further along it kind of it kind of
stalls it kind of stops I haven't seen
yet today with with today's models any
particularly successful auto research
roll out I I think research is one of
those tasks that is inherently
hard serial and long horizon and today's
models it's not very easy to glue it
from a small horizon thinking to think
about larger scale research projects and
auto research is one of the places where
we where we can where we can definitely
definitely see it so a although the
questions like I am asking myself is how
did humans master pursuing long horizon
goals very famously Andrew wild spent
seven years working on a single goal of
proving fermatas theorem he was
successful and was seven year project.
How do we how do we train our models to
do to do seven year sevenyear projects
and thinking thinking about humans even
more like I I've asked Chad GPT at which
moment did humans start developing
long-term planning and and what's what
what Chad GPT has told me that we have
until today roughly 10,000 generations
of humans since the moment we're able to
uh since the moment we're able to start
doing any any significant long-term
planning from since that time there was
roughly 120 billion people. So maybe
maybe this is it. Maybe we need 10,000
gradient steps and 120 trajectories to
sample and maybe that is what allows us
to optimize for for for long-term long
horizon planning as well as as well as
humans do. Uh also gradient descent is
more sample efficient than evolution. So
maybe we have even more and that's uh
that's something for us to to think
about and and revisit. The value
functions as a research direction is one
thing that definitely can help. It's if
if we got good value functions for AI
research, it will be extremely helpful.
I think the the research on value
function has been like at some moment we
we basically threw out value functions
when doing reinforcement learning on
large language models and everyone has
seen that it works as well. Value
functions are very very hard problem. I
have some amount of skepticism in in how
much progress we can do on on really
good really good value functions. Very
often finding good value function is
much harder than solving the problem we
are we are trying to solve. But if
someone figures out value functions we
are we are we're good. We can solve as
as as as long horizon problems as we
would as we would like. Maybe maybe
continual learning is the answer.
Continual learning tries to solve this
problem from the other side. We try to
update the model for the loop. If we
have long horizon, sevenyear loop, let's
prove this theorem and we repeat the
same thing every day, but we don't
repeat it with the same model because
the model updates on a new data. Every
day the model learns something, the
model improves and the model the model
gets better. I think continual learning
would be able to get us through that
very very well. The question the
question is how and this is an unsolved
problem. This is a problem that is worth
solving. And if if someone is looking
for for what do we want to work on right
now right here in this age of machine
learning I think having long horizon
agents is is absolutely one of the one
of the valid choices when we when we get
that technology we will be able to put
agent towards working on hard research
problems we'll be able to have them to
run companies this is a very long
horizon task that is that is very very
economically valuable and if I want to
delegate to an agent I don't want to be
telling it what to do every 30 minutes I
want to be able to to act on my behalf
for a long periods of time and I think
this is extremely valuable. So the the
research is not done uh there's there's
much much work to do and the objective
as agents that can keep going for us and
keep getting better over time. Thank you
very much.
>> All right. Thank you Jerry. very
fascinating talk. Uh next up we're gonna
have Dan Roth give a talk. He's the
chief AI scientist at Oracle and also a
professor at UPEN. Uh he's been a
professor for more than 20 years. Uh and
at Oracle he has a bit of a view into
everything going on in the AI race. So
please welcome Dan.
>> Okay. Hi everyone. Uh really excited to
be here. Uh so I'm going to change gear
a little bit and and talk about data,
how we use data, how we access data. Uh
and and you'll see in a minute why I
call this AI for data and data for AI.
But mostly I'm I'm really excited about
the promise that Genai has for data. Uh
so so really we are going to move from
the messy world of using a lot of types
of data, different representation,
different types
uh where people need to learn the
domain, need to learn how data is
represented, need to transform data from
one format to another and need to
understand how to fuse diverse data to a
much cleaner way where we'll be able to
actually work with data in a conceptual
level, our own terms, our own metrics.
uh and and what adds to this exciting
excitement is the fact that really a
large amount of data that exists in the
world is going to remain outside a
language model. So, so you know uh
language models have swallowed a lot of
the data uh and and you know this is why
we have powerful agents today. Uh but
but uh there's really no more general
purpose data. A lot of the general
purpose data has been swallowed as I
said by model provider already. But
there is a lot of data out there. Data
that belongs to corporation, data that
belong to financial institution,
government agencies, uh people uh and
medical centers and this data will stay
outside the models and it's going to be
dynamic. Uh so the question is how do we
deal with this external data and I think
that one of the key use cases of Genai
is going to be that of orchestrating and
supporting access and uh use of external
data. Uh and this is true for human
consumption but it's as important when
we think about agents using data. Think
about your coding agents. In order to
develop coding agents, these coding
agents need to access a lot of data from
design documents to tickets maybe to
correspondence about what happened in
previous generation of the software.
They need to access knowledge sources
and do something with this and and this
is difficult. So reliably supporting
decisions that depend on retrieving and
using data is is extremely difficult,
more difficult than we kind of think.
and and it's difficult for multiple
reasons. Uh it's difficult because of
information retrieval.
Hopefully this will move at some point.
Uh there is a myth that information
retrieval works but you know try to
search your email and tell me whether it
does work. Understanding information
needs understanding the store data using
data all these are extremely challenging
uh in today's world. Uh and it makes all
this business of knowledge access and
use very difficult. So most cases we are
thinking about AI for data sort of how
to use data or how AI can help us to use
data for our own human consumption. Um
ask what AI can do for you but really we
care about data for AI because in order
for us to develop agents agents need uh
to access data to access a lot of
different kinds of data. So this
relationship between AI and enterprise
data is really noted one-dimensional. Uh
while AI unlocks value from the data you
already have, the quality, the
structure, the governance of your data
really determines what the agents what
AI uh can actually do. So understanding
these both sides of these equations are
really important and really the
difference between AI that works and AI
that may not work. Um so really the data
layer underneath agents is crucially
important and and very difficult uh to
build. So uh so think about agentic
capabilities and what kind of data we
need in order to develop them. Think
about, you know, the 17 different types
of documentation that exist and think
also about just trajectory data,
operation data, tool use traces,
uh, and all this data that your agents
need in order to be able to actually do
what you want them to do. So why is it
so hard? Uh, there are many reasons for
this is hard. There are some core
difficulties. you know, retrieval
uh really information retrieval isn't
working unless the way you present the
information it is lexically close enough
to the way the documents that you care
about are represented which typically
doesn't happen. So this this actually
necessitates developing a semantic data
layer uh across knowledge sources. So
first of all you will bring the
representation of the data closer to the
way information either expressed but
also so that uh you will not care about
where is the data coming from which data
source it's coming from we need to deal
with structure so people think about NL
to SQL or NL to other formal
representation and this transformation
is very difficult partly because it
depends also on retrieval if we want
agents to use the data again we need
information to them to access multiple
knowledge sources and we need expertise
for each one of these knowledge sources.
We have rich documents today more and
more rich documents are being stored
from papers to figures to video to
images and the information inside this
rich data is actually not exposed to to
your retrieval unless you do something
to expose this information. Uh, and then
maybe some pre-processing, maybe some
stuff that your agents may or may not
do. As I'll show in a couple of examples
later on, planning to how to access
data, in what order to access it, how to
filter one source by another is a very
challenging problem. And not to mention
conflicting information. Think about
your file system or your email. How much
conflicting data is there? And we want
our agents that access data to actually
do something well with this. And of
course there are reasoning challenges.
Uh reasoning
uh in many cases is beyond the
capabilities of general purpose models.
And under all these kind of core
difficulties, there's issues that have
to do with governance, policy
enforcement, reliability, consistency,
auditability that if you want to use
large scale data in a context of a
corporation, medical center, and so on,
you really have to deal with and
optimization, you know. So in the first
generation we don't care so much about
cost but we do care about cost and how
to think about when do I process data
offline when do I process it at runtime
how do I cache computation how do I use
query logs and and history all these are
really difficult problems so uh we
actually are trying to work on all these
aspects of the data and I'm going to try
to give you one slice of this an
important one but not the only one from
the perspective of NL2 to SQL. And I'm
going to give a shameless plug to some
results that some of our teams at Oracle
have done in participating in
competitions like Spider 2 and Archer
and doing doing really well kind of
leading on top of the leaderboards in
this. But beyond the shameless plug, I
want to actually point out the absolute
results. So you can look at Archer H
where the results is actually 55%. or
spider 2 where the results is just low
70s which means that we are really far
from being able to address these issues
of accessing data and using data uh
properly. Uh and I'm going to illustrate
this with with the following uh example
that hopefully you'll find interesting.
So I'm very interested in tennis and I
follow tennis closely. So I'm using
tennis as uh as an example for a lot of
the things to kind of show capabilities.
So here is a question that I asked just
a few weeks ago. I presented to a top
model. Give me a list of the European
male tennis player sorted by their
tennis income.
Only tennis income. So if you think
about it's a very complex question
because the model needs to know who are
the players, which country they're
coming from, is it in Europe or not?
Then go to tournaments they play in
2025, how much money they made in each
one. But within and the model actually
give me the the way it thinks which
sources it goes to which tables it goes
to which pieces of text it goes to and
at the end it gives me a nice table. Now
first of all before I analyze the table
think about how cool it is. This is
really the promise. I just express my
information need in natural language and
the model devised it. He gave a plan
access many information sources
structured unstructured
uh web used its parametric knowledge to
know where the countries are and so on
reconciled conflicting information
because there's a lot of conflicting
information out there aggregated that
and summarize it into a table.
Beautiful. Now let's look at the
details. Look at these two uh entries
that I point to in the errors and you
see that they're not sorted correctly.
This was the most surprising mistake to
me because the model should have called
the tool to to do sorting properly.
Never mind. But even more interesting is
someone is missing. I'm sure some of you
will be able to tell me who's missing
from this list.
Alcarez is missing. So the model forgot
Carlos Alcarez. Not nice. Uh, and you
can also look at these two players that
I point to and you'll see that their
income is identical to the dollar. So
they made millions of dollars and the
income is identical to the dollar.
Cannot happen. Clearly a mistake. So so
what's happening here? So so really it's
it's a it's a very difficult task. You
the model needs to optimize access
across knowledge sources. Now, it can go
about it through a list of players,
generate a list of players, and then
figure out whether they're in they're in
a European country, which tournaments
they play with, how much money they made
in each tournament. Or it can go to the
list of tournaments and then look at
each tournament, who play there, how
much money they make, and so on. Now,
there's a lot less tournaments than
players, so maybe this should be the
right way. But on the other hand,
tournaments and data are more noisy. So
it really doing this right really
depends on understanding the data and
the domain. Uh which is very difficult
in tennis it's possible in most cases
it's just impossible. So while agents
are doing this faster than we can,
they're prone to errors and high cost
and and most importantly
if you think about it and I hear I I did
remind the model that he forgot Carlos
Alcarez and he added Carlos Alcarez but
if you look at it carefully you'll see
that a few other things changed. For
example, Andre Rublev number seven
completely disappeared from the new
list. The money changed a little bit. of
people someone zer that made over six
millions before now is making less than
six millions. So it's not consistent but
really the important thing that I want
to point out here is this is tennis
really who cares. Uh and I also know the
results so I know how to kind of look at
it and decide whether it's correct or
not. But if this was the same question
that you ask about your financial
analysis of your company or any other
sensitive information, the notion of
visibility or failure is really
important. We should be able to address
this issue because without it we cannot
use these kind of systems reliably and
and consistently. So I want to stop here
basically remind you that real world
data is multimodel, temporal,
multilingual, heterogeneous and we
really have to do a lot of work in order
to unlock this information and
understanding both sides of the
equations. AI for human consumptions
over data and and data for agent
consumption or using data for agent
consump consumption uh is really the
difference between AI that works and AI
that disappoints.
Thank you. [applause]
>> Okay, thank you Dan. Uh next up for our
last talk before the panel uh we have Wu
Chen who is a technical fellow and
corporate vice president of Microsoft
AI. He co-leads foundation model
development including their coding and
agentic models and he was the last
author of Laura the industry standard
technique for efficient LLM
customization. So Wu everyone welcome.
>> Thank you. Thanks.
>> Yeah. Good afternoon everyone. It's good
to be back here. So I think today I'm
going to talk about two very simple
thing. One is the what drive the
continuous model improvement
and the second one is the water nest for
the continuous model improvement.
So the first one for the continuous
model improvement I think everybody's
think about okay it's the it's the
compute definitely compute is the first
very scaling engines without a computer
you cannot do anything so basically I
think you can think about a lot of this
kind of improvement basically was driven
by the compute there's more compute
there and
so the model will become better
automatically if you train longer so on
the other hand edge you also this kind
the more compute you also unblock a lot
of this kind experiment and a lot of
innovation basically is also from the
experiment and also this kind the fast
iterations. So from the computer
definitely for today there's three
dimension for the computer today. The
first one is the pre-training.
Pre-chaining when you have the large
model where you have this kind of the
more data and for today is also more
exploration. This exploration came from
the model or it came from the human when
you explore more definitely you are
going to make the model better. I think
that is the basically a lot of people
call as a pre-training scaling law. The
second one is the post training. So for
the post training wise so definitely I
think for posting today a lot of simple
problem are already solved. So the
computer is more focused on how can we
solve the harder problem or how can we
solve the longer problem long horizon
and also how can we solve this kind of
the multiple agent problem in the
training. It's not just in the
inference. So basically we can also call
this as a post training scaling law. So
the last one definitely is the test time
compute is for the product serving. So
basically it's about how can you make
the this kind the coot this kind the
family of model interact together. The
other one definitely is the data. So we
always say data is the king. Everything
else is the queen and also data is
oxygen. So basically data you can think
about data is a second engine to make
everything happen. But basically there
are two kinds of the effort in the data.
One is the pre-chaining pre-chaining. So
if you go to see most of the
pre-chaining making progress is also
most of because of the data every time
at when you are able to clean the data
much better when you're able to refresh
the data because the web data is also
becoming better and better every day and
also have more and more coverage. This
kind of the synthetic data is not just
about the quality. The most important is
the coverage is able to create a lot of
complimentary data than before. So this
basically is also trying to make this
data much better for the model building.
So since data I will talk a little bit
actually I think is the most important
thing in the in the future. One of the
most important thing the second one is
the human data probably the all the data
we create every day will be the seed for
the synthetic data that mean data will
be the mainstream in the future and all
the data we have actually it just to how
can we produce a better synthetic data
the other the other thing about this
kind of the power training basically is
about this kind of the environment how
can you make the I environment to run as
the same as the user use that during the
training so I environment And we so
basically make the model to be more
useful for the product scenarios and
because RL needs kind of the tri error.
So definitely you need to make this very
similar thing in the infants get into a
training. So basically the model is able
to learn. So and so this is also very
similar as about how can you build a
simulation in the training. So you are
able to generate an Olympic datas. So
basically that's the key for this kind
of the I environment. The third one we
talk about is the model architecture.
This is very complicated. There's so
many paper about the model architecture
and there are so many detail there. But
I think I want to summarize basically is
about there are three dimension all
these times thing trying to optimize.
First one definitely you want to build a
much higher quality model. Second one is
the lower inference cost. So a lot of
people just ignore the second one and
the last one is definitely for the today
is the how can you support much longer
context make more efficient. So the goal
is also pretty simple. How can you make
it better and cheapest? So and based on
the this kind that I I try to believe
actually for data is more important than
the model quality model architecture
actually which pay more attention to the
inference cost and inference efficiency.
How can the model be more popular?
Finally is going to def is going to be
decided by how fast you able to run and
how cheap you able to run. I think
that's more important. So we need to
define the inference at the beginning.
The other one basically is based on the
GPU advancement. We need to put more
compute instead more I IO to less IO but
more compute. That's also important. The
next one I want to quickly talk about
actually is about a lot of people are
talking about is the distillation and
distillation basically we think about
for the machine learning a lot of thing
actually is just about distillation.
It's just about you are just dist from
human or you distear from model. When
you distear from human for example when
you learn from all these kind the
existing data in the web you distear
from human. When you learn from this
kind the product telemetric data you
also distear from the human this
interaction you also basically when you
ask human to label data for us actually
you also distiller their knowledge. So
distillation actually is a very popular
things. So with this DF model definitely
I think this is very yeah it's very po
popular as well and so yeah basically I
was think about thisation basically you
can think about in the industry is much
more efficient than this kind the
training is also yeah very we don't need
to build anything from scratch so
basically I I believe the nest better
model basically was built from the
existing model instead of trying to
build everything from scratch the last
one uh the next one Distlation is also a
very general pattern. For example,
you're able to build multiple teacher
because it's easier for the IIL to learn
from one single specific teacher and
it's also able to run in parallel for
this and steer into a single model. On
the other hand, I want to say
distillation have a lot of this kind of
the research have a lot of new problem
coming. It's not just about a simple
problem. is a very important problem for
and for example there are so many
different kind of distillation just like
you able to steer from strong model to
another strong model or you able to
steer from strong model to weak model
and basically you're also able to
distear from the weak model to the
stronger model it's also possible
there's also a lot of research we need
to deal with every day for example just
like a more powerful teacher model a
more powerful model doesn't mean it's a
better teachers that's very similar as
humans and also some weak model
sometimes also can be a very teacher
model. So everything is possible for the
distillation. The next one we want to
talk about is I definitely what I work
pretty well today is about it's very
efficient. It's very effective not
efficient it's very effective to solve
the problem. No matter it's verify
problem or nonverify problem it's also
very good for us to solve the product
behavior. If there's something wrong we
just define a grader. We just put some
data and then actually it's much more
efficient than other approach. And it's
also very good to work directly to the
real environment. But there's also a lot
of thing actually we believe I believe I
distillation and the sync data maybe is
good enough for us to get to the SE
improvement. So, but I think there's
also a lot of challenges for the IO as
well just like it's very slow and I
think a lot of breakthrough need to
happen to make it much faster and it's
also pretty the update is also very
incremental when you run the I chain you
will see the update is very incremental
just like maybe sometime the lower
update is already good enough so and on
the other hand actually is the data so
what drive the is the data s data
definitely will be more important for
the I training and I also believe maybe
99.9% of the data actually are coming
from synthetic data in the next step. So
I think we we already talk a lot about
the harness for today so I will be
quick. So and one thing I want to say is
about we should try to optimize the
entire system and harness is a very big
part in the system instead of trying to
optimize the model. So because there's a
lot of builder here I want to say so
before we think about to optimize the
model try to optimize everything around
the model the model itself. So before we
try to optimize the model and the other
thing is about I want to say the harness
you build today a lot of thing will be
observed into the model at some point
the harness will become simple and
simple simpler and simpler and we need
to define but definitely at the same
time we are also define more and more
complicated scenario and build more and
more complicated honeys is going to eat
a lot of thing there's nothing we're
able to change so for the last one I
want to mention actually it's very
important for us is about is we just not
care about the benchmarking we also care
about the production this kind the
usabilities
and usability actually this kind of
interaction data actually is very good
for us to build a better model it's not
just about this kind the benchmarking so
and by by default actually I think the
continuous model improvement really
require a continuous deployment at scale
a lot of people are going to use your
model and actually you're able to
understand what is going wrong And based
on this interactions data and also able
to see what other model do for this
scenario and get the insight and trying
to learn from there and this is my last
slide and it's about the a for the next
round I think first one is the scaling
is keep working and we also don't know
what's the ceiling and the other one
definitely the model should be is
already able to optimize the harness is
also able to optimize and change another
model I think that's also going to
happen because model is better and human
for this. And the other one definitely
we want to optimize the whole system and
the synthetic data will become the
mainstream for especially for the next
model training and the last one is also
very important. Human is their
involvement is still very essential. We
still need human to guide the model how
to do the model especially for the last
one how to make sure this set
improvement align with the human's value
instead of doing something the model
want to do. Thank you.
All right. Well, that was a fascinating
number of speeches and now we're
actually going to have a panel with all
of these people. So, uh, everyone could
welcome out all of our speakers. We're
going to have about a 20-minut
discussion here.
[applause]
All right.
[snorts]
>> Why can't you
>> Oh, we should think it in that order.
>> All right. Well, so we're very lucky to
have this group here. A lot of the
people here are responsible for the way
AI looks today in the real world. Um,
and everyone here is also working on how
it should look in the next couple years.
So, I think this is a wonderful
opportunity to have this discussion. um
we're not going to shy away from the
hard questions. So I guess the first one
is you know maybe just to start high
level like do we have the right
architecture to get to this next level
of AI? Do we have you know are
transformers the right thing to get to
RSI continuous learning? Um I think I
want to start with Jerry on this one.
[laughter] Let's start here.
>> Okay. It's a it's a spicy one, but I
feel like I'm being asked a lot about
it. And my my theory of AI research is
that you always should try to think what
is the bottleneck of the day? What is
the thing? Why are today's models not 10
times better than they are right now?
And while like doing what we've been
doing, keeping investing in
transformers, building new environments,
scaling up training like gives us gains.
Those gains are predictable. We already
know how to do it. I think architecture
is the biggest thing that can give us
gains beyond those things that we
already know how to do. I I I genuinely
believe and like you know record this
remember that the next two years will be
like the time of architecture where the
biggest gains and the biggest progress
in the deep learning will come from like
trying to step away from the
transformers. We have been like like the
discovery of transformer has been an
inflection point for AI research like
scaling transformers and doing
pre-training has been has been another
moment where where the age of scaling
has has started but transformer has has
carried us very far and I think it is it
is kind of like a little bit like
holding us back right now where I
believe for the same cost you probably
can train much better agent with a
different architecture just don't know
that architecture yet and it's a it's a
time to find it that's that's what I
Oriel, you guys are working a lot on uh
as you just said RSI. Do you think
transformers are the right thing to get
us there?
>> Well, first of all, I guess transformers
have transformed over the years. So like
if you look at the actual model uh today
is it's it it's resembles but it's not
the same. So every iteration of a new
model we see outside especially the ones
you can also see in the open source. I
mean there's a lot of tweaks in the
architecture already happening. So
definitely there's a hill climbing
perhaps to Jerry's point is a bit of a
local optimum around the transformer but
that's very important. Um I'm not sure I
would believe that I want I mean is
there a better transformer like thing
that is much more efficient? Possibly. I
I feel like when I think of
architecture, I think holistically, not
just the brains, but also the whole
agent that you build around it. That
architecture I feel has a lot of more
lowhanging fruits to optimize like its
memory system, how it compresses context
and so on. So I would probably bet on
disruption there first. Although I'll be
rooting for obviously better
architectures that I'm sure they'll
publish in Europe's 2027
or so.
No comment there I guess. Uh Don, I'm
curious for your thoughts on this.
>> Oh uh yes this is a very good question.
I was uh talking to Jerry earlier. The
question is which we will go faster. Uh
yes I think potentially there ought to
be some other architecture there that
will be more uh effective than
transformers. Um the question is um how
far so we have two path. one is we
continue down the current path with
transformers and then I think a number
of people here are working on RSI and so
on. So then with RSI as even with the
current path um the AI can continue to
improve and then with RSI then it can
help potentially to find better
architectures
>> then that's one that's one path and
another path is we have um we have
humans we have uh you know experts like
Jerry to try to um discover rights or
design new architectures and the
question is which path will get us uh
sooner there. Um especially given that I
think we can also do a poll here for
people to think like what they what what
everyone here thinks about the timeline
like when are we getting to RSI with
this path. Um and I'm actually very
curious to to hear.
>> Okay. Well, let's do a poll. Let's So,
who thinks we're going to get to RSI uh
this year in 2026?
zero. Uh, okay. RSI 2027.
Hands go up [laughter] or down. We can't
do Okay. 2028.
>> Okay. 2029.
>> So, I don't
>> 20 any hand.
>> Maybe you need to say the year. What is
what what year do you think RSI is
coming? So I'm not going to make a
prediction because I think this is not
necessarily the key question when you
ask about whether the technology is
ready for something. So so we are in an
agentic summit here and why do we move
to agents? I mean one reason we move to
agent is the really an admission by
model providers and everyone that that
we cannot think about just models we
need to think about systems.
uh and and uh so when we think about
systems today we are still coupling an
agent with a model but that's going to
change I mean so we're going to decouple
agents from models uh and you know the
architecture and is going to change also
at the model level but the system level
is the one that I think is more
important because people realize that we
have to be able to delegate we have to
use solvers we have to use experts
models and so on and to me the key
differences are going to happen at that
level.
>> Uh and you know over time transformers
also are going to change right? So
transformer is is a very very recent
beast.
There's no reason that in 10 years this
is going to be uh the the component that
we rely on. But still the question that
are around kind of how to build
intelligent systems with solvers with
expert system and so on that's going to
stay even when we change the the
underlying architecture of the of the
model itself.
>> Um yeah I have some questions for that
too. I think this is also another
question for debate is one um how much
of the power of the differentiation is
at the model level versus actually at
the Asian level and also um so we have
been doing some work I think uh like
others have been doing this work as well
so as the model becomes smarter and
smarter uh so right now when people
build agents there's still a lot of
human design yes we talk about memory
systems, compaction, all these different
things. You still have humans design
this. But as the model gets smarter, the
model essentially can build agents uh
themselves. So we actually recently
developed a open framework, agent
framework. We call it AIcentric uh agent
development framework where we have the
model to actually build agent itself on
the fly uh and build all these different
components and so on. And as the model
gets smarter and smarter, it actually um
can do this fairly well. So then there's
it also begs the question then going
forwards whether we actually still need
to build these uh yeah here we are at
the agentic summons but there's a
question whether even next year what are
we going to do are we just going to have
models to actually write the entire
agentic system framework
>> uh and so on.
>> Boy, I'm curious for your thoughts on
that. So few things. So um there's a
question about what's the mental model
for the AI development. And you might
think that maybe AI development is like
stacking up a Lego piece after piece
that is actually not even that hard to
make an improvements in the uh let's say
the memory piece or like uh having
architectures more efficient. It's just
like you keep on stacking it up and
models become better and better. Or
alternatively, you might be thinking
that actually doing AI research is
similar to developing relativity theory.
You need is like a genius like a massive
brain to come up. Uh so far historically
we have seen that primarily we are in
the world number one. There has been few
instances of this like a breakthroughs
like a transformer as people mentioned
but still we can keep on hill climbing
building Lego piece one after another
and it seems that the models might reach
the you can call it escape velocity. So
in some sense they can be good enough
such that they can continue stacking up
the Lego pieces. So you know you build a
model that gets 150 IQ then you get 200
IQ 250 IQ. Of course there is a question
about the asmtote if that would continue
and it might be the case that if it
continues for sufficiently a long period
of time it's like if it keeps on
improving then even if there are some
necessary u uh uh breakthroughs needed
then the good enough model might crack
them. So um now whether or not the
escape velocity would be achieved like
whether or not there's like enough
energy put into the system. Uh that's
the question or like when would that
happen.
>> Would you I'm curious for your thoughts
on this kind of you know system versus
you know the core architecture kind of
debate.
>> Yes. I think for the eyes I eyes side
basically is highly depends on just like
you say the system including this kind
the IO environment the evaluation which
kind of task you want to solve I think
from the model point of view as long as
you are able to specify the task very
clearly but I think this is pretty
challenging it's the most difficult part
and it's easier for the model for the
the ISI trying to okay specific to this
task is doable in the next two or three
Yes, but you want to say okay it's need
to be very generic. I I I think it's
much much harder maybe one 100x harder.
So there's a huge difference. Yeah. From
the architecture point of view I think
in my opinion is about architecture
finally is still defined by the model
capacity. how many parameter you have in
the architecture and yeah
so
nothing is for free for the architecture
def definitely no free lunch when you
get something good is going to sacrifice
the other part for a lot of case yeah I
mean I think just to kind of move the
conversation along a little bit with our
time I'm curious also like there's been
this incident recently in the last
couple weeks of you know that's really
brought to light how much Security and
safety is so important with agents
nowadays. Like you know we might not
have RSI today but agents are very
capable. We've seen you know OpenAI's
agent hack hugging face anthropic said
its agents have escaped containment too.
Maybe Don I'm curious for your thoughts
based on your security background. Like
I'm curious what you think you know how
these agent how these incidents shifted
your thinking about safety and security
with agents.
>> Okay great. Yeah thank you. Thanks for
the question. So first I actually uh
want to clarify some things. Uh so first
of all uh actually what the in the open
case what the agent was trying to do uh
it was tasked to actually solve uh tasks
in the benchmark exploion which is what
uh which is what we developed. Um so and
there have been various blogs written
about it. Um I want to take the
opportunity to clarify a few things. So
first of all that exploit the openi uh
deploys exploit gym in their internal
infrastructure and so that's their
entire their internal deployment and
also so the agent what the agent did was
somehow the agent figured out oh maybe
uh you know in in order to solve the
tasks um maybe hugging face has some you
know data uh or information related to
this. So I went to decided to go to
hugging face to try to find this. And
then actually before this incident
became publicly known, we actually got
an email from uh from hugging face
>> asking us oh there's so we also develop
another benchmark called cyber gym. uh
so cyber gma and explor actually covered
the entire like the life cycle for
vulnerability uh like a vulnerability
discovery and then exploit generation.
So, we actually got an email from
Hagenface asking, "Oh, there's a cyber
gym uh like a
essentially serving points
um and they seem to have some
vulnerabilities
uh like asking us do you guys know
this?" And then and then we looked into
this. We said, "Oh, actually this is not
our subject." [laughter]
So basically some third party um
deployed some some service on hugging
face and they also called it severe. I
think they copied probably some things
from the cyber gene benchmark and but
they called it cyber gym and uh and then
in the end that's actually what the
agents was able to exploit and then
through that and then got into hacking
face infer and so on. So, so, so, so I
wanted to clarify that even though that
one was called the cyber gym, but
actually is entirely a third party uh
department has nothing to do with us.
Um, so we actually clarify with the
hugging face, you know, for their blog
and so on. But anyway, so this I think
is a wake up call. uh even though the my
group so we have been among the earliest
to actually investigate in this space um
looking at the impact of frontier AI in
the landscape of cyber security and we
did all this work also I was trying to
essentially raise the awareness earlier
for the community to get prepared and to
take action because I could see even you
know we started working in the space
actually two years ago and even then I
could see with the AI fast progress and
so on. This is what's coming. Um
although actually I had to say even
though we build out this benchmark and
demonstrated I was trying to talk to you
know people even in the policy space
that we need to get prepared but I think
it was difficult for people to really
understand and get the message. So I
think what happened was so mythos
certainly helped uh and also I think
this incident really
>> right
>> it's a wake up call for people that the
agents capabilities now are have reached
a level um [clears throat]
>> yeah so so I want to say that you know
it's it's clearly a wakeup call
>> but but I think it's we we shouldn't uh
think that this is only the cyber
security problem this can happen
everywhere
>> so so we we saw earlier today the Tetris
example
uh but you know imagine that you have a
multi- aent system that and and the
agents communicate among themselves and
you impose some constraints on what
information they can communicate to each
other. So so Don doesn't want some of
the information that her agent has about
her to be communicated with Max agents
or my agent. Now we can we can put a
verifier that that verifies that they
don't break these uh these kind of rules
of what can be communicated but you know
the agents can go around it and maybe
change the language that they're using
so that the verifier is incapable of
verifying what they're doing. So so this
issue goes much beyond just cyber
security. It goes to to any
communication system that involves
agents and we have to really think about
it from from kind of uh from basis what
are the issues that we have to deal with
and and I think we are a little bit
dormant in this space.
>> Yes, absolutely. I think yes the the
risk is uh is vast um you know covers
broad a broad broad range and I think in
cyber in particular I think just um
given that already we know there's huge
incentives for attackers to attack and
now really with frontier AI
significantly reduced their uh
essentially costs and also the expertise
uh level that's needed and so on so this
can really uh bring a huge sea change in
the case
>> boy check from a resilience perspective
what do you
>> so so I was thinking what's the mental
model of what's happening now and maybe
one mental model so so okay it doesn't
seem that what just happened is like a
last incident okay that doesn't seem so
okay quite opposite it seems that we are
entering a new era okay so um maybe one
way to think about it is imagine what
happens if all of the sudden and locks
to the houses stop working. Okay, you
can just enter every house. What
happens? Okay, so that's what what what
uh that's the era that we are entering
with cyber security. uh we should expect
in the very close future that the open
source models will become insanely good
in uh uh uh in uh cyber u and that will
be a problem that will be a problem for
critical infrastructure uh it will be a
problem both from perspective of
teenagers hacking for fun uh people who
are motivated to hack for their um uh
gains and also nation states
and all of these will be at play. My
guess is that it will be chaotic.
>> Any other thoughts from from the panel
here? Uh I I think like cyber security
is one angle and definitely we probably
already live in the world where like we
are lucky that open and tropic are good
guys but they probably can hack any
company in the world if they want to
which is which is a scary realization
but there there's other angle from a
perspective of reinforcement learning
researcher which which I am a little bit
worried which is which is misalignment
and and and reward hacking which we
which we have seen there and and
escaping the sandbox and that that's
something that everyone who works on
reinforcement learning I would like them
to be really really care about and
really really worry about because in
some ways we are training those models
to get reward in various environments in
various situations and it's up to us the
the the researchers the trainers the the
people building that systems what what
is actually rewarded and whenever we are
building an environment where the mold
can hack where the mold can do
analytical things can the model can do
incorrect things to get reward the model
will do it The model will learn it. The
model will express that behavior in the
in the real world and we are putting
more and more of our life in the hands
of the models and we'll be only doing
more and more. AI is great and everyone
is using it and the reward hacking
models if they are exposed to the real
world they will be doing things that are
are not not great and they are trained
for that by us. So like designing your
environments in a way that promotes the
right types of behaviors and the right
types of taking actions is what really
everyone should be doing. And I I think
there almost should be like some
standards. You don't get to train your
malls if you don't build your
environments carefully enough because we
don't want to be having misaligned malls
everywhere that are trying to exploit
whatever whatever sandbox they are in to
get the to get the reward. It's a it's a
really really scary thing to think
about.
Well, on that note, uh we are out of
time, but thank you to the panelists for
a great conversation. If we get a round
of applause for the panelists and thank
you so much everyone. Appreciate it.
[applause]
Hello.
Good afternoon. Whoa. Sorry about that.
Um, it's 3:30 in the afternoon. If you
think you need some coffee, trust me,
you don't. This session is good. It's
going to be electric. We'll keep you
awake. I promise you uh there's some
fantastic speakers we have lined up. U
but let me just quickly uh introduce
myself and what we're going to do over
the next hour or so. So my name is Guru
Chahel. I'm a partner at Lightseed
Venture Partners and I'll be chairing
this session on robotics and world
models. Um you know at Lightseed we've
been investing across the AI stack from
Enthropic to uh Mistrol to SSI to
reflection uh and robotics companies
like Dexterity and Skilled and others
for a very long time. And this vantage
point has given us a front row seat to
what's been happening in robotics and
world models. And a common view today is
that robotics is still in its pre-hat
GPD moment. And you'd probably agree
with that. But we also think that the
inflection point may be closer than most
people realize. Um over the past year,
we've seen meaningful advances in
foundation models, um world models,
simulations, data generation, and
training techniques that are beginning
to translate into actual real world
deployments. And that pace seems to be
accelerating. So over the next hour,
we'll explore what's driving that
progress, where the technology stands
today, what's still missing, and what
will it take to make robotics truly
mainstream. Now we've put together an
outstanding group of speakers. Uh we'll
begin with a few technical talks and
then bring everyone together for a
fireside discussion. Uh with that it's
my pleasure to introduce our first
speakers Sergey Lavine. Sergey is a
professor here at Berkeley and a
co-founder of physical intelligence
where he is building generalpurpose
foundation models for robots. He's one
of the most cited researchers in robot
learning and he'll speak on robot
foundation models. Please welcome
Sergey.
[applause]
>> All right. So, like many of you, I like
to use uh uh LLMs to help with all sorts
of things that I need to get done. So,
last night, um I came home, I was pretty
tired after work, and I asked my
favorite LLM to help me out a little
bit. I asked it to help me, uh clean the
house, fold the laundry, and make
dinner. Uh, unfortunately this didn't
work. Although it told me all sorts of
things that I should do myself. So what
I'd really like is so that next time
when you have a request like this, there
is an embodied system, a foundation
model sitting in a robot that can
actually do it and not uh just spit out
a bunch of texts at you about what you
should spend your evening on. Now
fortunately robot foundation models are
quite an active area of research these
days. Uh this is an area that's fairly
young but is growing very rapidly.
Physical Intelligence, the company that
I and my colleagues founded, has been
working on this for over two years at
this point. And there's some nice
results. You know, this is a robot
making a coffee using an espresso
machine for 13 hours straight,
assembling boxes in a factory. Lots of
folks are working on this. There are
amazing results coming out from other
companies, from academia, from many
different places. And when I thought
about what to speak about in this talk,
I figured maybe instead of showing lots
and lots of results, I would zoom in on
a particular technical challenge with
these robot foundation models and some
ways that we can start addressing it.
Because underneath all the demos and all
the results, um there is a big question.
Why is it that with all these really
nice results, we aren't seeing robots
that can follow arbitrary prompts all
around us today? So typically when
somebody does research on robotic
foundation models, they might have a
task like this. Uh put the corn in the
pot. This is from the bridge data set.
It's a fairly rudimentary kind of uh
research grade uh uh robotic system and
it's doing the task. That's kind of
nice, but that's not really what we
want. What we want is something like
this where the robot actually goes and
cleans your house and the prompt is not
like pick up these shirts and put them
in the hamper. The prompt is I've got
guests coming this evening. Given that
line of text, the robot should
understand what it is that you want and
act appropriately. Meaning that you have
to uh complete the prompt that specifies
an entire job, not just an atomic task.
Uh and it's not just about instructions.
You need to make a plan and you need to
generalize skills to the new context and
really handle this correctly, including
the context where your slides go out in
the middle of the talk. Um Oh, wow. Uh
it does depend on the people in this
room. Yes.
Um, so anyway, where was I going with
this? The um, uh, the command is also in
context. So the fact that you've got
guests coming, like the way you
interpret that depends on what the robot
knows about you and your home and all
this other stuff. So the point is that
there is a lot of grounding and problem
solving that goes into making this work
for real beyond just the one atomic
task. Now, a really powerful tool for
this is test time compute. Uh, hopefully
many of you are familiar with what this
does in LM world. Test time compute is
how we can solve complex problems by
thinking about them harder, generating
more tokens. It's a way to solve harder
problems, but it's also has a less
obvious benefit, which is that it can
break down an unfamiliar problem into
more familiar pieces. So if you tell the
robot, I've got guests coming that maybe
the robot has never heard you say that
before, but it can process the text,
semantically reason about it, and break
it down into things that it can actually
do all the way down to like pick up this
t-shirt.
So you can endow robotic foundation
models with test time compute to get
them to be better at problem solving. We
started working on this a number of
years ago. And the key here is that it's
not just about solving a harder problem
going from an observation to an action.
The model can break down the task into
bits that are more in distribution
relative to other parts of its training
data. So it can say like, hey, you're
asking me to pick up this object. I've
never done that before, but what I have
done before in my webcale pre-training
is localize objects in images. So maybe
I can localize an object in an image and
use that as a stepping stone. Break down
an unfamiliar problem into more familiar
steps.
Here's an example of this in action. Uh
again, this is a research grade task.
It's not particularly realistic, but
it's kind of a nice nice for isolating
the issue here. Uh we're asking the
robot to make the blue block the only
thing on the plate. And obviously
there's something sitting on the plate
right now. And you want to react in a
way that is correct, but also
semantically sensible. like you don't
want to pick up the sushi and put it on
the table because that's a little bit
unsanitary. It's a toy sushi, but maybe
the robot doesn't know that. So, the
sushi should go into a semantically
appropriate container. And the the
reasoning trace here actually takes care
of that and even figures out that the
sushi might be a little unfamiliar to
the robot. So, it should actually output
a spatial coordinate instead of directly
relying on the action output to take
care of that uh visual distribution
shift. And then when we run this, the
thinking trace is updated every few
seconds based on what's going on. And
you can see that this thing kind of does
it. Now again not the most sophisticated
or impressive demo but more to isolate
that particular bit of the problem. And
of course you can optimize these
thoughts. Thinking models are most
powerful when the thoughts are optimized
with reinforcement learning. And here
again reinforcement learning serves a
dual role which is it curates the task
specification and turns it into
something that is more familiar relative
to the robot training data. Uh which
means that you could propose a number of
different textual uh commands to break
up a highle prompt and pick the one that
the robot is most likely to succeed at.
Uh a little example of this here in the
top row. The robot was commanded to put
the hammer on the plate. I don't know
why you'd want that, but for some reason
you do. Very unfamiliar out of
distribution task. And if you use an
off-the-shelf vision language model, in
this case, this is Gemini, and you ask
it to do this task. Gemini doesn't know
what the robot can or can't do. So it
says, "Yeah, like go ahead and put the
hammer on the plate." The robot doesn't
know what a hammer is or how it goes on
the plate, and it messes up. After
reinforcement learning, the model
actually kind of um spoon feeds the task
to the robot say like, "Oh, move a
little to the left so that it's right
over the hammer." And then when you tell
it to put it on the plate, there's
really only one option, which is to do
it right. So reinforcement learning
helps to bridge that distribution gap.
Now, so far we've talked about thinking
in language, but that's not the only
tool available to us. If you're like
cooking a recipe or something like that,
it makes sense to think through the
steps in language. But imagine you're
rock climbing. You probably don't think
like, hey, I'm going to move my arm 37
centimeters to the left. And you it's
more natural to think about this
spatially in terms of locations, in
terms of what things will look like in
the future. And you can have robotic
foundation models that think in other
modalities. Um, again, this is some
older work uh in a kind of more
researchy context, but we had some u
work on following instructions where
instead of breaking down the instruction
to t text, you break down the
instruction into an intermediate image.
essentially imagine an image of what
things would look like if you make
progress towards the task. That's your
thought and then condition on that
thought. It's easier to take the correct
action. This works very well because of
course the image generation can be
pre-trained on lots of internet scale
data associating language with images
and enabling the robot to imagine
substeps.
So to bring this back to large-scale
robotic foundation models, the last
thing I want to tell you about is some
recent work from physical intelligence
on large-scale models that think with
multiple different modalities. So this
is one of the features of the PIO7
model. It's a large scale vision
language action model that incorporates
a lightweight world model into its
decision-making process. So it reasons
about a task in language and in images
and then grounds all of that down into
actions. So here's a little demo we did
here. Uh Lucy is teaching the robot to
use an air fryer. We intentionally made
sure that we didn't train it to use the
air fryer. So it's an unseen appliance
that has to generalize to out of the
box. If you tell it to air fry the sweet
potato, it actually succeeds, although
it takes quite a while and kind of
fumbles with it quite a bit. Uh but if
you give it a little bit of additional
supervision, it can be much more
reliable. And crucially, the supervision
is not in actions. Lucy is going to talk
to the robot in words and will actually
explain the task step by step just by
coaching it. And that adds additional
data of images with language. The
actions here are not ground truth. The
actions are taken by the robot. And
after this coaching, which is used to
fine-tune the thinking process, again,
there's no ground truth action here.
It's just uh teaching the the robot how
to think essentially. Now, it can use
these multimodal reasoning capabilities
to do the task quite fluently. So what
you're going to see is the text which is
now generated by the model itself and
you're also going to see images which
are intermediate thoughts that the model
is generating to help it do the task. So
here's the the language thoughts and
underneath it is the image thoughts. And
now the robot can do this uh sweet
potato air fryer task pretty reliably.
So that's kind of an illustration of how
multimmodal thinking can actually make
for much more powerful robotic
foundation models that generalize more
broadly uh even to new appliances that
they haven't seen before.
So, some takeaways, uh, thinking or
reasoning models can allow robots to
generalize better and follow more
complex prompts. And I think in the long
run, that's going to be really important
because we're going to want these things
to follow much more elaborate prompts
than, uh, what anybody is doing now.
Prompts like, you know, you're a robot
butler, clean the house at 6 p.m., uh,
you know, get dinner ready, uh, do my
laundry on Saturdays. Like, that's the
prompt. And it might take the robot uh,
weeks uh, of operation to fully do that.
Um, the thinking doesn't have to be in
text. the physical world is complex and
you should use the right modality for
the job. And I think that there's a lot
of really exciting developments we'll
see over the next few years in
multimodal thinking. Um, and we can even
use multiple modalities simultaneously
to think at the right level of
abstraction so that if you're following
a recipe to cook, maybe that's in
language, but if you're uh, you know,
uh, figuring out how to use a new
appliance, perhaps you have to imagine
where your hand should go to push the
button or to open the container. All
right. Uh so this would provide both a
way to solve harder problems and more
effectively transfer knowledge from
other sources that might be represented
in different modalities. Um I'd like to
thank both uh my students at UC Berkeley
and my colleagues at physical
intelligence who carried out most of
this work and thank you for listening.
[applause]
>> Thank you Sergey. Uh great that was a
fantastic start. Next we have Jim Fan.
Jim is the director of robotics and a
distinguished scientist at NVIDIA where
he leads the gear lab on generalist
embodied agents. Uh his work covers
robotics that learn in simulation and
transfer to the real world. His talk
today is called the robotics endgame.
Please welcome Jim Fan.
So let me take you back to a new
conference in 2017.
Ali Rahimi walks on stage and he gave
one of the most interesting talks I've
ever attended. He said machine learning
has become alchemy. And he was right.
Nothing was rigorous. Everyone was
vibing. Things seemed to work but nobody
could tell for sure. The future feels
fuzzy and fragile. But here we are nine
years later. The LOM folks are now
speedr runninging AGI on the back of
mythical beings literally called mythos.
So what happened to alchemy? I would say
two curves. Two curves is all you need.
The first curve is the neural scaling
law. More compute, more data goes in,
the loss goes down. So predictable that
you can forecast what you'll get before
spending a single dollar. Now this curve
turns alchemy into mathematics. In fact,
it's the guiding light for how trillions
of dollars of investment should flow
and the second cler just landed today
this year. So the x-axis is still
training compute but now measuring a new
currency called tokens. This is auto
research where models self-improve with
more and more agents running experiments
on their own and capars causes the final
boss fight for LMS.
Now the beautiful thing is these two
curves are not separate and in fact you
can stack them together. A gentic
scaling starts where foundation scaling
ends. So what started as alchemy is now
the most reliable curve that
extrapolates into the near future.
Now as a roboticist in this LM party I
have a confession to make. I feel so
lonely, so left out. Why can't us
roboticist get a piece of that fun?
And that is because robotics is stuck in
the age of alchemy.
And we're not going to make it until we
figure out what to scale and what
happens at scale.
And let's dive into two things. Model
and the data strategy. You know for
digital AI the first pre-training
paradigm is next word prediction.
And I thought the second pre-training
paradigm would be something glorious.
But it turns out we give it a name AI
video slob.
I mean I can watch fat cats playing
banjo all day. It's peak internet. But
no one's going to take this seriously
until we figure out that these video
world models are learning to simulate
physics internally. So these are videos
generated by Nvidia Cosmos 3. And you
can see that the model picks up gravity,
buoyancy, right? Reflection, collision,
all by just predicting the next blob of
pixels at scale.
And an emerging property is you can even
solve visual puzzles. So, Cosmos solves
the puzzle on the left by running
simulation forward in pixel space. And
now on the right hand side, that's my
favorite. Watch closely. Cosmos finds
that if you're not looking, geometry is
optional.
Geometry is just optional.
So, how do we turn these world models
into something useful for robotics?
Introducing a new type of policy model.
on the upper right corner what you see
is not a real camera feed. It is
actually the robot dreaming what's going
to happen in the next few seconds in
video and then acting on top of that. So
the policy is robust. You can perturb
you can knock things over and it just
replans and redreams on the fly. And how
it works is we take a pre-trained video
diffusion model and we have it jointly
decode video and action into the future.
And we call this new type of model world
action models or webs.
Now these models only dream a few
seconds into the future. But for real
task you need longer memory. So we
introduce a new technique on top of
these models to extend the native
context length of the model a 1000x to
8k time steps and that is 5 minutes
worth of muscle memory.
So how it works is this technique called
TDT or test time training. It embeds a
tiny model inside a model and at
inference when the incoming signals flow
into the model it takes gradient steps
on this tiny core and then it keeps
compressing the history it sees into the
fast ways. So basically the robot is
able to continue learning after
deployment
and you see here it is fully autonomous
right a single shot of the robot
assembling this car from scratch
and what it also enables is in context
learning from human. So here you have a
human demonstrating how to reconfigure
this circuit board into something novel
the robot has never seen before and
conditioned on this long video prompt
lots of tokens in context. The robot
imitates what a human does faithfully.
And of course, we discover a new scaling
access. That is the context scaling.
Performance goes up reliably as we get
to 8,000 time steps. And that's three
orders of magnitude beyond the prior
state-of-the-art.
Now, how do we scale the data that goes
into the system?
The last three years were the golden era
of teleop VR headsets, these complex
rigs that look like medieval torture
devices, you know, so much investment
from the industry, so much pain and
suffering into something that
fundamentally does not scale. You guys
drive Tesla,
you know that when you are driving
Tesla, you are contributing data to the
biggest physical data flywheel in the
world, right? And the beautiful thing is
you don't even notice it. The data
upload is an ambient process. So we need
the FSD equivalent for robot
manipulation. We need data collection to
fade into the background. Stay out of
the loop so we can organically capture
the full glory of human dexterity across
all walks of lives. So we are going all
in on human egocentric videos with these
detailed annotations like fine language
and hand poses.
introducing ego scale where 99.9% of the
training happens on human egocentric
videos. What you see here is a fully
autonomous policy that maps directly
from pixels here from the eyes to 22
degrees of freedom humanlike dextrous
hands. And how we're able to achieve it
is we pre-train on 20,000 hours of high
quality in the wild videos and then we
fine-tune on only 50 hours of mocap
glove data and four hours of teleyop.
And that tallyop is less than 0.1% of
our training mix. And with this, Eagle
Scale is able to perform dexterous tasks
like sorting poker cards or long horizon
tasks like manipulating the syringe
using only a handful of demonstrations.
And I can't leave you without another
scaling law. So the fascinating thing is
we discovered a neuroscalating law for
dexterity.
There's a very strong relationship
between the amount of human video data
we put in and the optimal loss. It's
actually a clean log linear mathematical
equation and we hope to scale this to 1
million 10 million and maybe someday 100
million hours and hope this law
extrapolates.
So that completes the first part where
x-axis here is the compute and yaxis is
the robot capability. So we showed how
to scale up robot foundation models end
to end by gradient descent on sensory
data. Now, how can we carry this curve
even further?
So, here's a very simple idea. We
realize that all the simulators and
robot control stack, they're just code
after all. And I'm excited by this
because finally, we can copy homework
from LMS.
We can turn robotics into a bunch of
coding environments
that basically takes as input motor
actions and outputs um sensory signals
and then decades of robotics libraries
and perception stack. They can now be
integrated as agentic tools.
So let me take you to our lab at night.
There's not a human inside
and all you can hear are motors humming
and GPU spinning. So it kind of feels
like night at the museum. You know, the
robots all come online alive. They talk
to each other through code. They tinker
with a control stack, run experiments on
the real robot, and they even go online
and read papers. And in fact, we found
that our robots read a lot of Sergey's
paper. So thank you so much, Sergey, for
contributing to our agentic token
budget.
And how it works is we give a team of
coding agents a robot fleet and a very
simple goal to solve a task as fast as
possible subject to safety constraints
and make make no mistake. So here every
robot station is trying a different
research idea
and to do to do the loop engineering
successfully we need three things. We
need to auto reset a physical scene,
auto improve the policy and auto
evaluate. And once you get those
correct, the agents will be able to hell
climb a task from 0% all the way to 99%
success rate. And it's our first attempt
at physical auto research.
So, I was just telling my team the other
day that my dream is that we can all
take a holiday and our boss doesn't even
notice
because we can just be reading the
reports from the agents and my team
said, "Be careful what you wish for."
And we can do it the other direction.
Instead of solving a single task, we can
let the robots autonomously discover
skills as they try to solve a huge
variety of task in simulation and in the
real world.
So this work, recent work called Aspire
enables a new type of continual learning
where it does not update the weight
matrices of a model, but instead it
learns a skill library that compounds
over time that captures the know-hows of
how a robot practitioner would do.
And it also unlocks a new type of
scaling law. And here the x-axis is
still training compute but now measured
in tokens and the y-axis is a number of
validated skills. And we found that
aspire learned skills are able to
transfer from sim to real and even
across embodiment.
So compute equals tokens equals skills.
And that complete our full curve.
Total robot intelligence equals
foundation intelligence plus agentic
intelligence.
World action model sets the floor and
physical auto research raises the
ceiling. So if you take away only one
page from my talk today, this is the
northstar that governs how compute is
going to drive progress. Or as a wise
man would say, the more you buy, the
more you save.
>> [applause]
>> You know,
[applause]
to me, solving robotics
means passing the physical touring test
across a wide range of tasks. You can't
tell the difference between whether a
human or robot had done that task.
It's deceptively simple. But this is the
next, if not the final grand challenge
for AI.
And judging by how sexy the robot just
went out, I think work has cut out for
us.
Now that leaves us with a final skating
law for today. It's been 14 years since
the first forward pass of Alexnet to
Opus, Methos, GPD souls of today. And if
we add another 14 years, that brings us
to 2040.
I think humans are terrible at feeding
the scaling curve because looking
backwards it seems flat but looking
forward is almost vertical.
Physical AGI will happen gradually and
then suddenly but first we need to
figure out the guiding principles the
scaling laws to govern the field so that
we can turn the practice of robot
learning from alchemy to chemistry. All
>> [applause]
>> right, I know what you're probably
thinking. Two amazing talks by Sergey
and Jim. How do we top that? I assure
you, we're about to. Um, next up, we
have Mika Spranganger. He's the
president of Sony AI. Now, his team
built the GT Sophie. That's a
reinforcement learning agent that beat
the world's best drivers in Gran
Turismo. Um, for those of you not into
video games, that's a racing video game.
Now, he's he will show you how those
same methods move from games into the
real world. My one advice, do not blink.
These videos are amazing. Please welcome
Mika.
>> Hi there. Um, so I'm going to tell you a
story for that we built at Sony Ei over
the last five to six years where we took
reinforcement learning, we built racing
agents in game, beat the best drivers,
put them into product and then use
exactly the same infrastructure, the
same AI agent factory to solve problems
in the real world.
And so it starts, everything starts in
2022 when we released our first nature
cover on this project that we did on
Gran Turismo, which is a racing game.
It's a 30-year PlayStation title led by
the visionary Yamochi, who really is
interested in recreating the sensation
of racing. It's actually not a very easy
game to play. Uh you have to really hone
the skill of driving in order to enjoy
this game. And what we did is we built a
reinforcement learning agent to beat the
best drivers as a first step.
And if you look at this race, this is a
race from an actual competition against
one of the best. There's more people on
the track, but in this instance, against
one of the best drivers in the world,
I'll challenge you to tell me which of
those two cars is driven by an AI versus
a human.
And I think you can't because we've
built this AI to be a really interesting
competitive but in some sense also
humanlike driver. In fact, the car
that's driven by AI is the gray car and
the white car is driven by Muchian
who is a world champion in Gran Turismo.
Now, Gruntism is a very very interesting
benchmark test for us because it
combines
physical realism.
The game itself is built around a
physics engine that really recreates in
highfidelity
cars and their physical properties on in
some cases real world tracks.
So, there's a physical realism. So, if
you want to do racing, the first thing
you have to do is you have to master
driving a car. Now, it's not just
driving a car, it's racing a car. And
racing itself is really at the edge of
control. It's sometimes going over this
edge of control and pushing the limits.
The second point is you're not alone on
the track. You have to manage tactics.
If you make a move against an opponent,
that opponent will counter counteract
your move. And so you have to learn how
to deceive, how to test your opponent.
And then finally, sports etiquette,
which is also very interesting. Racing,
I would say, is a interesting sport
because it's a sort of collaborative and
competitive dance. You're not really
supposed to crash into other cars. At
the same time, you have to drive very
aggressively because otherwise you're
just going to be taken overtaken and
lose the race. And so, we trained an
end-to-end system to solve all of those
things at the same time.
And of course, we use reinforcement
learning. So, I think many people in the
room will be familiar with this. We
essentially use the game as the
environment. We get inputs from the
game. Those can take different forms
from visual to state representation
similar to an autonomous car. Uh, of
course, the agent takes actions in the
game. And then also there's a reward.
And the reward, as you can imagine, is
if you're fast and overtaking, that's
great. If you crash into other cars,
bad. If you're not really making
progress on the track, trace on the
track, bad. And so that alone is enough
for us to build these highly
specialized, very very capable AIs in
Gran Turismo and ultimately also in
other games. So we'll need some
infrastructure for this. So we worked a
lot with PlayStation, obviously the
maker of the game, but also PlayStation
infrastructure. The game itself only
runs on PlayStation. So we have to use
cloud infrastructure of PlayStations to
get the scale of compute that we need in
order to build those agents. Now, we can
train those agents once we're done with
the research relatively fast. So, after
15 minutes of driving, we can basically
get around the track and then it takes
about 24 hours to get to a really,
really nice driver.
But ultimately,
oops, that was a bit too early. Uh,
ultimately it takes a few days to train
a superhuman policy. Now, what does
superhuman look like?
So this is a track called dragon side se
dragon trail seaside and uh this is just
against the time. So it's a time trial
example but what you'll see is something
coming up called the chicane of death
and this agent is taking this in a
superhuman way. No human driver has
taken the chicane which is going to come
up right now
in this way. Okay
but so that's the physical realism
learning how to manage [music] the car.
This is also very interesting. Actually,
let me go back for a second here and
start from the beginning. What you'll
see here is the agent tactically trading
off positions in order to have a better
entry and then exit in the curve. In
fact, we're going to see a double
overtake by AI. White cars driven by the
humans, colored cars driven by AI.
There's going to be a double overtake of
AI to humans.
You can see sort of the cars starting to
trade off positions here in order to
have a better entry.
and then double overtake
exit into the into the curve. Right? So
these really subtle differences, these
really tactical choices of when to trade
over a position uh in order to have a
better entry exit that's also completely
learned. Anyway, so all of this is
enough to train agents to be really
really successful, super human,
successful, superhuman, beating the best
esports drivers in the world. Now for
us, that's not enough. We're actually
very interested in building agents that
are fun. And so we're going to listen to
somebody that is also a high-end racer
tell us about what she learned from the
AI.
>> It was really interesting seeing the
lines where the AI would go. So there
were certain corners that I was going
out wide and then cutting back in and
the AI was going like in the whole way
around. So, I learned a lot about the
lines and also um knowing what to
prioritize. Like the AI into turn one,
for example,
I was breaking later than the AI,
but the AI would get a much better exit
than me and beat me to the next corner.
Um, so I I I didn't notice that until I
saw the AI and I was like, "Oh, okay,
cool. I should do that instead." Of
course, this is reinforcement learning.
So in game, we can also train many other
types of behaviors using exactly the
same framework. So changing the
objective from going very fast to
burning as much tire as you can gives us
superhuman drifting agents.
Now, okay, so that's all great. It's all
fun and games. Uh obviously part of part
of uh us being a part of Sony is also
this opportunity to ship these products
to millions of people. So after the
nature paper, the team worked very very
hard on many iterations of this
technology, integrating it into the
game, six months after the nature paper,
all the way to something that I'm very
proud of, which is a power pack. The
first ever paid power pack for Gran
Turismo where people pay directly for an
AI experience. Because it's such a
human-like experience, we can have
longer races, we can have more fun
races, and PDI decided to build a power
pack around this new capability. And now
people pay directly for new AI
experiences in this space.
>> So all right, so this is the PlayStation
part, the simulation part, the Gran
Turismo, the racing part of the story.
Now, I've told you that essentially
we've built a system that we can apply
not just to racing, but we can also
apply this to different games, different
titles, open world titles, casual games.
But the thing that we did this year, or
that came out this year, I should say,
is taking that same technology and
applying it to table tennis. And table
tennis obviously has many fundamental
similarities with racing. In the real
world, there's physical realism. You
have tactics. There's an opponent that
you have to beat. Um, and so building a
factory for agents that can solve these
highly specialized competitive tasks
uh is something that we showed with this
work as well. And so I'm sure all of you
know table tennis. Uh this is one of the
trainers that we use to uh train the
robot. The ball is moving across the
field literally in the blink of your
eye. The ball's rotation, the spin is
the main difference between professional
and amateur players. The ball spins at
about 9,000 rotations per minute. Uh
reaches speeds up to 100 km an hour. And
all of this in this interaction, right?
So you have to master the physical skill
and at the same time on the other side
of the plate there's somebody who's
trying to beat you. And then of course
you may have surprising situations. And
so this video is going to slow down in a
second because the ball hit the net.
Something we did not foresee in training
or couldn't train for. And so within
fractions of a second, this endto-end
policy, there's no programming here.
It's completely trained end to end. This
robot has to react to this new
situation, change the plan that it made
at microscond level. Okay.
Now the similarity with GT Gran Turismo
doesn't stop there. In fact, we use a
simulation, a custom simulation for
table tennis to train the policy and
then bring it onto the real robot
without any changes and just play
professional players that uh using that.
So this is really cool. This is one of
the top players that we beat with this
robot, Mu Hilano. uh really really
successful table tennis player and I
think this is the second point. So she's
gonna make that point which is going to
be fun
and she's gonna be very happy about
that.
So that's great. Unfortunately uh for
her ultimately she's going to lose that
game against the table tennis robot. And
uh in the meantime we've tested this
system against many many players and we
essentially have a flywheel now where if
the robot still loses to a player
because of an unforeseen or
unexperienced tactic. Uh we can use the
data from that game to retrain the
policy overnight and then have a robot
actually beat that player.
And so the argument I want to make here
is that I think world LLMs are great. I
think world models are great. We should
not forget about reinforcement learning
and its ability to build highly
specialized
uh policies that can solve task in the
real world and in simulation at
superhuman capacity. And I think it's a
combination of all those technologies
that's going to ultimately help us to
solve the big big problem of physical
intelligence. Thank you very much.
Awesome. Um, great. Uh, next we have
Anastasis Germanis. He is the co-founder
and co-CEO of Runway. Uh, that's one of
the leaders in generative video and
world models and they put out amazing
demos. If you haven't gone to their
website, his team treats video
generation as a path to systems that
understand the physical world and his
talk is titled real world super
intelligence. Please welcome Anastasis.
Hello everyone. Good to be here. Um so
today I'm going to be talking about some
of the work that we've been doing at
Runway. um focusing a lot on both video
generation but world modeling uh
increasingly uh and I'm going to also
talk about some of the early uh early
progress and uh early work that we've
been doing in robotics in particular.
So I think everyone probably here is
familiar with this graph. Uh every every
year the horizon the time horizon that
uh a coding LLM can solve uh various
software tasks has doubled every year.
Uh there's been an incredible amount of
progress happening in the language
domain and in particular with the coding
agents. Um yet there is this uh this
contrast.
There is this incredible progress
happening in math and in coding. Uh but
uh some of that progress actually
doesn't transfer as well to tasks that
have to do with interacting with the
unpredictable uh real world. Um so
whereas there is every day we hear of a
amazing um you know an unsolved problem
conjecture uh uh being being um being
disproven. uh uh we still like LM still
fail at rudimentary tasks such as uh
running a vending machine business
effectively
and I think the reason why is um really
has to do with uh how effective we train
those models uh for coding and for math
we have this luxury of having sandboxes
that we can run at infinite effectively
infinite scale um and so we can scale
scale rollouts inside sandboxes like
very very easily. Um for a lot of the
real world problems that we care about,
we don't have a simulator that we can
run very easily that we can scale
rollouts. Uh and it's very time
consuming and very expensive to scale
rollouts in the real world.
And so one way of approaching this and
this comes to no surprise given the the
panel and the section that we're in is
is this idea of world models. Um and a
lot of people are familiar with world
models from the uh the David Ha paper of
the in the 2010s. Uh but actually that
that concept goes back into the the mid
20th century in cognitive science um and
some of the early uh RILL kind of model
based RL work as well and it's
effectively this idea that the way we
operate as humans is we constantly
predict and try out things in in our
heads. Uh we try out we try to
understand what the outcome of actions
that we take in the world will be before
we take those actions and that helps us
plan uh what to do. But in order to do
that effectively with agents, we need to
have this simulator of experience that
uh an agent can can use to predict what
happens if the agent takes specific
actions. Um and when it comes to real
world experience, what is the best way
to bootstrap such a such a simulator?
I think video is the most general
modality that we have that allows us to
simulate real world experience. Um there
is it's the most abundant uh kind of
source of kind of real world um um uh
scenarios. It teaches uh it can teach us
about physics. It can teach us about all
the tasks that humans care about. And
video is even more of a general
representation than that. Um it's not
just about real world kind of human
scale video that's captured by a camera
but it's also video can be used to
represent uh observations scientific
observations from many different scales
um both temporal and spatial scales. Uh
and it can also be used to to uh capture
observations from the digital world
which is especially relevant if you want
to teach agents to work with the you
know variety of interfaces
um that we we use every day.
And so our approach at runway has been
predicting the world by predicting the
next frame. Essentially we believe that
pixel uh frame prediction and pixel
generation is the right auxiliary task
to train uh at massive scale and build
models that have really powerful
representations of the world. Uh and
then you can use those models for a
variety of downstream tasks that you
care about in uh in the real world.
And so just to give a sense of like
where the quality of video generation
has gone, um I'd like you to take a
moment and kind of look at those two
videos and just uh think if you can tell
apart which one is one of them is
generated, one of them is real. Um can
you tell apart which one is which?
That's correct. I think the the right
hand is indeed generated.
What about this one?
I believe that it's the left one this
time.
What about this one?
Uh so the left one is generated in this
case. Um but so we run this as a user
study. We run it with a thousand
participants and uh it's actually
reliably less than 10% of participants
could tell apart what was generated and
what was not generated. Um so whereas if
you're you know if you're very familiar
with video generation uh if you if you
look at those videos for a long time you
will be able to tell apart which one is
real and what which one is not. It's
becoming more and more difficult. So
from a quality perspective we've really
kind of crossed some threshold where uh
it it's easy to trick human perception.
And so that has been a very long journey
over the past uh decade or so of like
increasing um kind of increasing the
compute and data scale that we put into
video models. Um so these are some of
the some of the milestones. Um gen 2 was
the first text to video model we ever
released a few years ago. Um and gen 4.5
is the is the latest uh the latest space
model that runway has released. Um so
there is a massive improvement in the
ability of those models to simulate
physics to have dynamic motion uh to
really um to to really feel like very
plausible real world video.
And so there's been all this amazing
progress in for creative video
generation. But how much of this
progress actually translates into the
stuff that we care about for physical
AI?
It turns out there's quite quite a lot
uh video generation can be used to
simulate a lot of longtail scenarios
that are basically impossible or
incredibly expensive to simulate
otherwise. And we have pretty robust
ways of measuring that. Uh obviously
there's a lot of work in physical uh
evaluation. Uh but there is some really
great benchmarks that allow us to uh
really compare real world from generated
uh real world video from generated
video. um and across a lot of different
categories of contents of of physics. So
from solid mechanics to fluid dynamics
uh to uh thermodynamics and optics
and even there when it comes to actually
um you know beyond plausible video if is
if it's actually physically accurate we
see that increasing compute scale um
really reliably improves the physics of
those models. So, so video models are
quite, you know, uh, like the the bitter
lesson really applies to video models
and we've see that predictably across
all the video models that we've trained.
And so the next stage towards actually
making those models useful for the real
world is making them realtime and
interactive. Uh, for a lot of the use
case that uh are relevant for real world
problems like in robotics, that's a very
important thing. if you either want to
build a simulator or a policy model on
top of video model.
And the way we do this and and our
approach is really taking the foundation
video model that we have the base uh
kind of diffusion model that generates
video uh in a that's birectional
uh and making it auto reggressive and
causal. Um and then um doing another uh
stage of distillation to make it to make
it real time. Um, and what this allows
is making the model interactive and
allow you to explore counterfactual
scenarios very easily. If I take this
action versus this action, what's going
to happen? And you get frames generated
on the fly based on the actions that you
take.
And there is this increasing trend as
we're building world models of improving
the increasing the generality of the
world models and also increasing the
flexibility of the world models. So one
of you know the early world model in the
original paper of David Ha uh was
trained on a particular kind of racing
game. Uh there were a lot of work in
world models specific for narrow domains
like in self-driving kind of footage uh
um so generating kind of road uh cars
moving in the road um to uh world models
that released last year like Genie that
were really high fidelity kind of mostly
static environment uh allow static
environment navigation um and a lot of
the progress that we've been focusing on
has been how do you make those world
models is actually dynamic. How do you
uh allow um you know simulating not just
navigating a static world but actually
taking actions in the world and ideally
taking actions by multiple agents. So in
in this case you have two different
agents that are uh basically you
instruct at the same time and you're
simulating uh simulating kind of the the
outcome of that.
And one of the variants of the world
models that we've really released has
been in robotics specifically. Um so
this is GWM robotics which uh is an
action condition video model uh that's
specific to uh simulating the outcomes
of uh actions of single arm or bmanual
arm robots. Um and we've seen that in a
lot of cases the rollouts that are
generated by those models are again very
difficult to tell apart from um you know
uh ground truth teleop data for example
and it's able to simulate very fine
grain interactions with uh cloth or like
other kind of non-rigid objects
and what this allows is making
evaluation much more scalable um
essentially you can use any policy model
which could be a VA or another policy
model uh and you can predict what
happens as an outcome of a particular
action and then feed that back into the
policy model
and what we've seen is that um those uh
GWM robotics and the world models that
we're building for robotics actually
match the real world quite well. Uh so
if you take a policy model like a kind
of pi 0.5
and you uh you have some ground through
teop data and you're rolling out the
exact same actions in um in in a inside
the world model uh you're you're seeing
like very good correlation between task
success in the real world versus
simulation. And so you're able to
massively scale like how how fast you
can evaluate uh policy models by doing
that inside the video model instead of
doing that in the in the real world. Um
and in the future this becomes also a
great foundation for doing uh RL inside
the world model and being able to scale
interactions uh much further or much
faster uh than you would in the real
world.
And one of the most important aspects of
building world models is this ability to
simulate failure. Um if a lot of
traditional video models have this bias
towards success, uh it's much more easy
to generate a video of someone shooting
a goal successfully and uh than than
not. Uh but that's something that's very
important when building world models
because it's very if you want to uh
evaluate how well policy works, you want
to be able to reliably uh have the
policy model fail if if it performs the
wrong actions.
So the ultimate goal of world models is
really to increase the number of
observations that uh we put into it. We
believe uh that learn simulators is a
much uh more uh scalable approach
towards uh you know building uh building
environments where you can train agents
uh in in situations where it's very
difficult to build kind of uh
traditional simulators by to author them
by by hand um or it's very expensive to
actually u perform those actions in the
real world and gather data.
And that's all in my end. Thank you for
your time. [applause]
All right, the last but not the least
talk of the day. Our last speaker in
this block is Wei Jean, chief scientist
at Applied Intuition and co-director of
Berkeley Deep Drive. He works on world
models and end-to-end autonomy for
self-driving vehicles. And he brings
that research into production at scale.
And for those of you who are wondering,
autonomous driving might be the largest
atscale production use case in modern
robotics. And so I'm excited to hear uh
what he's going to share with us. Please
welcome Wei.
Thanks for the introduction. Good
afternoon everyone. So today I'm going
to talk a bit about end to end autonomy
which is the first mass massively
productionized physical AI in the real
world.
So we want to talk about how we can
enhance such kind of autonomy with
something without imitation just with
reinforcement learning which is a bit
counterintuitive to the mainstreams.
So for those who are not super familiar
with applied intuition.
So we are premier physical AI technology
provider covering various kinds of
industry verticals including cars,
trucks, agriculture, mining,
constructions with autonomy stack, OS
simulation tools and broader physical AI
infrastructures. We are a 15 billion
valuation company with over a thousand
engineers. We are also conducting
cutting edge research on reinforcement
learning world models with applications
to autonomy and robotics with many
publications in top venues including
some award-winning papers.
So for the paradigm of L2++
ADAS it has converged to imitation
learning based end to end with mass
production and some of the leading
players also conducted post training
with openloop reinforcement learning to
bring the safety and robustness of such
autonomy into the next level.
Engine autonomy is expected to be
trained with close super reinforcement
learning in a world model that can
generate reactively generate some um
like surrounding behavior and visions in
a reactive way and this is how the
paradigm is shifting for autonomy from
the AV 2.0 openloop scaling to the AV3.0
closed loop scaling.
So at applied we've been creating the uh
high throughput reactive world model to
support large scale close to
reinforcement learning for end to- end
autonomy without imitation and such kind
of paradigm has achieved great
performance.
But the question is is there a smart
even smarter way to achieve this? So our
approach is try to decouple learn to
drive and learn to see. So here is how
we are doing this. In phase one we try
to learn to drive by exploiting large
scale cell play reinforcement learning.
Actually just now uh Michael just gave a
very good example on how cell play is in
empowering the uh autonomous racing and
I'm trying to give an example how this
is empowering the autonomous urban
driving
and in the second phase we can try to
utilize a super robust and generalizable
selfplay expert to teach another end to
end autonomy to align its output of the
driving behavior. here.
So for phase one, learn to drive, we
created Terra Zero, which is a selfplay
reinforcement learning framework that is
much faster with much higher throughput
than other state-of-the-art driving
simulator and selfplay framework.
Actually,
we are just utilizing some um public
data set scale map diversity while it
can still obtain 25 centuries of driving
experience with zero human
demonstrations.
And actually we can easily scale up such
kind of uh numbers into two to three
orders of magnitude higher by scaling
the GPU compute as well as the map
diversity.
So the policy trained from terra zero
can achieve state-of-the-art on various
closed loop planning benchmarks which is
vector based. So it's setting a clear
edge to the imitation learning based
planners especially on the ones that is
non-saturated with corner case only such
as the interplan benchmark and it can
handle various kinds of challenging
driving scenarios with desirable actions
with zero shots generalizability across
the global cities
and that concludes the first phase Learn
to drive. Second, let's talk about learn
to see. We proposed terror transfer
which is training a autonom end to end
autonomy taught from another uh experts
trained from selflay which is terror
zero. What we are trying to do is to
align the latent as well as the actions
for both of them with the same driving
cases from the offline data set.
And such kind of terror transfer end to
end autonomy without any imitation in
its training recipe can obtain
state-of-the-art driving performance on
the closed loop end to end driving
benchmarks setting a clear edge to the
other imitationbased methods tackling
various kinds of intentionally created
challenging driving scenarios with
surprisingly robust driving behavior.
So that concludes the talk and the key
takeaway is the autonomy paradigm has
been shifting towards the close of
scaling which is AV 3.0 know and both
the end to end and vector-based planner
can achieve the state-of-the-art with
like cell play or close reinforcement
learning only uh training recipe without
imitation and actually the cell play
close RL with reactive world model that
is not just some post-training technique
actually they are very powerful
pre-training techniques for autonomy
development
and the throughput for reinforcement
learning framework and the world models
can be a decisive factor for such kind
of paradigm for closable scaling.
Thank you very much for your attention.
[applause]
You should stay. Yeah, we're we'll all
get together.
Thanks Ray for the wonderful talk. Uh
you might know I certainly do that we're
running a little bit behind on time. So
we're going to reduce the time for the
panel only slightly because we don't
want to cut out the good stuff. The good
news is my superpower is I talk really
really fast. And you'll see I start a
sentence really fast and then I was like
no guru you got to slow down. So we'll
see today I won't arrest myself. I'll go
really fast. coming up to order.
>> Okay, this is an incredible group. Um, I
was going to start as you know with a
question around what's your definition
of world model. We will not do that
because that's the next 20 minutes
[laughter] of individual definitions.
Maybe if we have time at the end, we'll
come back to that for a sec. But I
figured we'd just dig right in um into
some of the meteor topics. Uh I listened
to all of the chats today and I picked
out a few where I figured there might be
some perhaps not disagreement but
slightly different stances. So I figured
we'll just have a discussion. This is
not one of those here's the question.
Let's go down the p that's I can't stand
that god. So let's start with physics.
Uh and asus in your chat your thesis was
just by generating video you can
generate an inside the model an inherent
understanding of physics and you showed
us some videos. um why do you believe
that? And then as you think through
that, I'd love for anyone else on the
panel who's got a contra view to weigh
in as well.
>> Yeah. So I think that's mainly an
empirical conclusion from just scaling
those models and u measuring how well
they perform on different uh physics
related tasks. Um in general our
approach has been if you want to
introduce inductive biases to make sure
that the model learns something well
introduce those inductive biases in the
data that you're training on. Don't
introduce them in the architecture. Uh
so we we have very intentionally you
know tried to learn everything directly
from pixels and not introduce any kind
of you know 3D uh 3D b kind of 3D based
priors. Um, and we've seen that work
pretty well. Like at some at some level
of scale you get pretty good geometric
consistency. That's something you can
also measure quite well. Um, and so I I
I don't think there is um a fundamental
reason in my mind that why that won't
continue scaling.
>> Someone has to take the other side of
this. Is it true like just generate
video and you got spatial knowledge
inside suddenly a model and becomes a
world model.
>> So I know Duru you said um you don't
want definitions of world model. Let me
still have one and then I can ground the
discussion. So for my definition, it is
a model that predicts the next sensory
state conditional actions. Now I think
video is convenient. In fact, video is
one of the sensors. It's called an RGB
camera. But on a robotic system, you can
have more than one RGB camera. And in
fact, you have a lot more sensors. And I
would say there are many modalities
missing in today's discussion on world
models. In addition to videos, there's
tactile, there's force, there's the
there are the invisles that we also need
to put into these models to have a
really holistic simulation, right?
Holistic capture of how the dynamics
should evolve. So, I would say video is
convenient. Um, video is easy to scale.
It's ready abundant, but that's not the
full story.
>> Okay, Sergey, you've done so many robots
now that are actually in deployment. One
of the few folks here who's closed the
loop uh along with Jim on exactly what's
happening in real life. What's your
view?
>> Um, I guess what I would say is that
if you generate videos that people find
compelling, I think it's very easy to
get into a situation where you get a
video that looks very good to people but
doesn't actually reflect a model's
ability to simulate the kind of
counterfactual effects of physics that
you would care about. Um so uh what that
means is that um
when you give a model a prompt, it
doesn't have to produce a prediction
about what will happen to a real
physical system in that situation if it
does something. It just has to produce a
a result that to you looks like a good
reflection of that prompt. Which means
that the model gets to choose and that
choice is actually very very uh
important. It gets to choose how to set
everything up so that it looks good to
you. Whereas if you need to actually
plan and act in the real world, you need
to handle the actual situation you're
in, the actual plan that you're making
and whatever kind of counterfactual
effect you might have. So uh what this
actually comes down to whether the model
actually understands physics or not as
Anastasio alluded to has to do with the
data of course. It's just that the data
that we would use to get really great
videos is not the data that we use to
get counterfactual. If you train a model
on uh really good uh driving data and
then you ask what happens if I like
drive into a building, it'll probably
produce the building morphing into a
beautiful road and you're driving
happily down the road. And people have
actually done this and that's exactly
what happens. Right.
>> Uh so I think that the answer is like
yes, the model can handle physics. You
have to be very careful not to let it
fool you.
>> Right. Right. And while staying on this
topic of you know what goes inside the
model I want I also want to I'd love a
little bit of debate on sort of we
constantly hear or we're certainly
hearing now the and this I'll start with
you Jim the era of uh VAS is over and
the the future is world action models um
do you hold this view Jim if so why? And
then I'd love for more panelists to
weigh in. Is VALA is it WHAM? Is it
both? Or is VA dead? And it's all WHAM
going forward.
>> Absolutely. Yeah. I I know I talk a lot
about what action models, WAMS and VAS.
I think it depends on the level of
abstraction that we work on, right? So
there's the system one and system two
thinking. System one is fast and
reactive motor skills. System two is
reasoning, right? Like you know coding,
tool calling, all of that. So I do think
wham is a very promising approach for
system one because many of these
physical common sense right let's say
how do you grasp a cup it's very
difficult to break down and describe
every frame through language tokens it's
just quite difficult from a first
principle point of view now regarding
system 2 I would argue that opus you
know GPTs they are actually VAS
these models are agentic they take
actions
I would argue these are VAS and in fact
more people use VAS than they use WHM
today because VAS also serve other
purposes and that is the part where I
discuss in my talk right agentic scaling
I think that's going to play a big part
right the VA which is which are like the
opas and the GPTs of the world they're
able to understand the world through
some perception and then calling tools
and be able to help auto research so I
don't see maybe one completely replacing
the other but It's really about the
abstraction level that you operate on
top of,
>> right, Sergey?
>> Um, I actually think that it's slightly
the wrong question. I mean, it's the
right question for you to ask us, but
it's maybe like slightly the wrong
question for like a researcher to ask
themselves. Um, because it kind it puts
the model before the data in a way that
maybe is not actually quite right. So um
the key to build a really good
foundation model is to uh be able to
productively ingest lots of very diverse
data and uh video data is one of those
data source and it's a great data
source. Uh now most uh VAS that are
actually good they are trained on video
data lots of video data it's just
they're trained on it in an uh in a
webcale pre-training phase which trains
the understanding backbone. Uh so I I
actually don't think that the right
answer is to say like oh is it VA or or
is it video it's how do you use the most
data and then on top of that there's
some like kind of inductive bias but you
know um as Ike used to say inductive
bias is train data in disguise. So the
effect of inductive bias might be large
when you're testing things at a small
scale but it dissolves away once you
scale things up. So really what we
should do is say like okay we're going
to leverage as many data sources as
possible and then be pragmatic about
what kind of outputs the model has to
leverage them
>> right
>> where you're um sorry Mika go ahead
>> yeah maybe I can add like two points
from my from our perspective so the
first one is um if you think about the
task that we are working on like racing
and table tennis I think language is
actually not all that helpful um it
doesn't really you can describe how to
to do the skill but there's very little
information I mean there's in cognitive
science there's this classic distinction
between declarative and procedural
knowledge, right? So, in order to ride a
bike, you actually have to do it and you
have to learn the physics of it.
>> Um, the second one I would say is like
if you obviously vision I think is a
great, you know, thing to condition on.
At the same time, in some applications,
you can't. So, for instance, if we are
in game and we're shipping a game to a
customer and there's like 20 agents
racing, we cannot render from 20
different viewpoints. There's just not
enough compute, let's say, on
PlayStation to do that because most of
the compute goes into rendering for the
customer like the player. And so it's I
don't think you know these are not sort
of yes no questions. They're sort of
like okay what is the domain that you're
interested in? What are you trying to
solve? What's the application
downstream? Um I will say that you know
having large foundation models that can
capture visual knowledge and language
model is in many cases really really
helpful but we also still need to
distill you know the thing that we're
actually interested in in a particular
moment and then maybe ship to a
consumer.
>> No I like that answer. It's not an
eitheror. It really is use case
dependent and both have you know really
sort of interesting applicability. Um we
>> sorry one one more thing to add on the
one versus uh VA discussion is that
generally there's a lot of convergence
that's happening towards omnimodels that
can actually predict both uh both visual
modalities audio modalities text
modalities and so ultimately it's kind
of to to Sergey's point it's all about
like what are you specializing the model
during pre-training on are you
specializing you know is the data mix
biased towards more low-level motion
planning is it biased towards high level
reasoning so it's it's less about um if
the you know it's it's less about one
more or va architecture it's more about
like what like what what are you
dedicating the capacity of the model
ultimately um and that tends to be the
important factor
>> right um way backstage we were talking
about robots and simulated data and
stuff like that um today
you know from what you're seeing how
much of real robot skill has to come
from things like reinforcement learning
in the physical world versus the digital
world. Um, and I'd love to then this is
one of those questions where I'm sure we
all have a point of view. So, I'd love
to start with we and then maybe go down
the line.
>> Yeah, definitely. So, a great question.
So, I I want to separate that into
different applications. On one side for
autonomous driving, so we care more
about the behavior as well as the visual
modality. And for those two, it's
relatively easy for us to scale that up
from the real world data and inject that
into the like synthetic world with a
more scalable way. And for that part,
right now it's more like this. Many of
the leading players for productionized
like end to end um like ADA system is
mainly focusing on utilizing the real
world data while some of the synthetic
data can be utilized for the
post-training stage. Well, we can see
the trend that large scale synthetic
data can play a the key role or more and
more important role for making the
autonomy to be more robust and safe.
While on the robotic side, uh I think
what I learned at this at this very
point is that for tasks related to local
motion for whole body tracking. So the
reinforcement learning based methods can
be pretty useful and even dominate that.
Well, for complex task like uh dextrous
manipulation, it could be a bit hard for
us to either create the uh high fidelity
synthetic world capturing many of the
key physics uh attributes or define a
good reward function to really train the
corresponding policy in closed loop. So
at this very point what I saw is that
behavior cloning or imitation based meth
methods are still dominating.
>> Right? Let's fine-tune this question
Sergey as we as we come down to you a
little bit more. Um let's say there are
certain tasks you just have to do in
that robot's embodiment extreme
precision in data collection versus
simulation egocentric data videos etc.
What is that distribution? How much of
one do you need and how much of the
other? Are we still in the age where you
just need to do the task over and over
again a million times or can you do a
vast majority of the work either sort of
in silicone or through egocentric data
etc. What are you seeing in real life
now? Well, I I think there's there's two
two sides to that scale to the scales
there. There's the the supply side and
the demand side, right? Uh and this is
where I think the future is going to be
very different from the present because
uh in the present, I would say that in
robotics, we're like in the bootstrap
stage where we're trying to figure out
like what would it take to get uh models
for robots to be good enough so that uh
they can actually be used with endto-end
learning. But we won't be in the
bootstrap stage forever. Eventually
we'll be in the stage where there are uh
as many robots deployed out there as
there are a you know vehicles on the
road today uh and there will be very
plentiful sources of data from robots
interacting with the world autonomously
and then reinforcement learning methods
that can use that real world data will
be tremendously important. Um the other
thing here is that um the challenge
increasingly as the imitation learning
methods that you mentioned get better
and better will actually be how do you
bridge that last gap? How do you go from
a 98% successful robotic policy to 100%
successful policy? And there the domain
gap is really important because you
really want everything to line up to be
absolutely uh ideal. So there I think we
will also need reinforcement learning in
the real world. But I think that that's
like that's what's coming in the future.
I don't think that's the state today.
Like I think your summary is an
excellent summary of the state today.
>> Yeah. Jim, you I know you've done some
experimentation on this. What are you
seeing? Yeah, you know, guru, I think
great scientists invent, greater
scientists copy. [laughter] I absolutely
love to copy homework from LMS. I look
at them all the time. So, what are the
OM folks doing? I think they are not
just creating data anymore. They're
creating environments. It's all about
acquiring millions and millions of
coding environments and then doing RO in
those environments so that we can get
the methos and the GPD souls of today.
That's how they got here. Not through
imitation learning, eventually through
reinforcement learning. So I see
robotics to do something very similar
that we need to build environments. Then
what are some options for environments,
right? Option number one is you run in
the real world. I think Sergey and Pi
has done exceptional work over there.
Absolutely important, right? The physics
perfect because it's directly in the
real world. And then option number two
is classical simulators, right? like you
know Isaac Sim of the world but those
simulators the bottleneck is not the
simulation speed in fact the simulation
runs very very fast but it's the assets
it's environments it's the task that we
used to need a lot of artists to curate
but now there are recipes called real to
sim that I believe is super promising to
automatically scan the world and
transport the real world into a
classical simulator so you can both be
datadriven while also relying on a
classical fast physics solver. So that's
option number two. And option three back
to world model. I think one very
practical use of video world model is to
use that as a neuro simulator. It's a
datadriven program by data neural
simulator. Then it can take as input
actions and then generate videos and
sensor states effectively using it as
environment. But the thing is it's going
to run very slow but it will have a huge
amount of diversity as much as a world
model can afford. So ultimately it's
going to be reinforcement learning
across these three options for robotics
using different types of compute using
different constraints. So I would love
to see this as a more holistic approach.
>> Right. Um as we come up on time I'm
going to ask two sort of rapid fire
questions that I love. So first question
we'll start with you and ask us the most
amazing demo in robotics or world models
you've seen recently not from your
company or team. [laughter]
>> I've seen some great things internally
but uh yeah um
one demo or one one uh model release I
really like was by I believe the it's a
new startup called induction labs. Uh
the model is called Photon one. Um and
it's um effectively a world model of uh
based on screen recording. So a digital
world model of sorts. Um and they they
showed that you don't need um you know
ve very often like when you're training
computer use models or you're
postraining uh LMS to do well in
computer use uh you leveraging a lot of
kind of your text supervision in
addition to um to kind of directly like
screen uh frames from uh UIs or or
screens. uh but they they trained the
model entirely on essentially a video
model on just screen recordings and they
were able to show that um they actually
get competitive performance with uh with
Gemini on computer use or like Gemini
one of the small Gemini models uh with
uh with an order of mic to less compute.
So I found that pretty impressive.
>> I think that says more about the nature
of of work we do on a screen than
[laughter] than anything else. Uh Jim,
something that made you go, "Wow."
>> There there's actually a robot that
millions of people already buy and use
on daily basis. Um it's called Tesla
FSD.
I've been driving Tesla since last year
and honestly I was amazed by the latest
versions and uh you know it's all like
rush hours. You can see right the policy
it's able to negotiate super well in
super crowded lengths. uh almost
humanlike and I would say sometimes even
better than I would have driven myself.
So that gives me a lot of hope because
that is one physical system solving a
very important task autonomous driving
and once you spin that physical data
flywheel you get these huge performance
gains a quantum leap compared to a
couple years ago. So that's why in my
talk today I also stress the importance
of having data collection fade into the
background. The data collection cannot
be intrusive. And that's why when you
have egocentric data on humans, you are
able to capture this dexterity without
interfering with what they're doing. And
that's the way that we can draw a
parallel with FSD and maybe some decade
there for robotics.
>> I would say that's the example. That's a
great one. Mika. So, I'm going to pick
something which is uh not robotics
itself, but uh general intuition
recently released um a world model
really for Rocket League, which is a
game where cars play soccer. It's kind
of funny game. Um what's amazing about
that breakthrough, which I think is
about two weeks old or so, uh was that
this world model could render
consistently four different player views
in that world. Right? So, traditionally
world models are sort of like it's me
with the world, my actions in the world
and uh that sort of unlocks um sort of a
multi- aent kind of multiplayer
potentially interaction of multiple
humans in the world um kind of future
which I think is actually very important
because we we often think in robotics
purely about the task performance
lifting a cop you know screwing
something but the world is full of other
agents um it's full of things of people
or AIs that we'll have to interact with
and So, I think this I didn't actually
think it's going to happen so soon. I
was thinking more like six or 12 months
out um that this is going to happen, but
I think that's like a major stepping
stone in in the right direction.
>> That's a great example. Sergey,
>> I have an example where there's kind of
a moral to the story. So, uh a while
back there was this video that was uh
that kind of went viral of um the Boston
Dynamics uh humanoid um Atlas doing a
backflip. And it kind of went viral
because it was around the same time
where there was a lot of this was around
CS, so there were a lot of demos of
humanoids and people were making fun of
this because it does this backflip and
it doesn't quite stick the landing and
it sort of freaks out and does this like
really weird unnatural motion but then
stays upright. Um, and uh people were
saying like, oh, like you know, Boston
Dynamics is having all these problems.
Look at all the unitry robots doing
these perfect back flips. But the folks
that work on rob on robots looked at
this and they realized that actually the
the Boston Dynamics video is way more
impressive because it actually doesn't
fall. like it freaks out, something
really horrible happens and it stays
upright. Then you remember this is 170
kilogram robot. It's way heavier, way
more complex than the more lightweight
Udantry robots. Uh and I think the
lesson there is that well besides that
Boston Dynamics has great controls
engineers is that with robots the demo
is never quite what meets the eye,
right? That the challenge is often not
the things that you see in the demo
reel. It's the degree of generalization,
the ability of the system to handle
unfamiliar situations and failures and
also all the complexity behind it. So
it's often easy to be misled by the demo
and not realize what the really
challenging problems there are.
>> Spoken truly like a person solving real
world use cases. I love it way. Yeah, I
would like to echo uh Jim for the Tesla
FSD which is also taking over like most
of my uh daily mileage and actually
there is a even uh more impressive thing
that I saw uh for that company I cannot
disclose the name because I I was on the
R&D car of that but that company can
achieve uh similar kind of level
[clears throat] performance in super
crowded kind of uh street with a lot of
lot of like uh pedestrian cyclists or
other kind of challenging situations.
for 1 hour without any intervention from
the driver side. while the onboard
compute of that car is only 17th of the
uh Tesla like hardware 4 kind of compute
and with like even simpler kind of uh
sensor switch on the vehicle and for the
robotic side I think one interesting
thing I saw in the Acura and the CPR uh
booth this year is uh a Chinese startup
called Sudu which is also trying to push
the boundary for how to utilize the
synthetic data. It's doing a lot of like
generalizable kind of pick and place
tasks with right zero shot kind of
thing. Just let the audiences throw
arbitrary things onto the table and do
that.
>> Right. We're almost out of time. I have
to ask this one question. The answer has
to be a number. So, we don't have time
for anything else. Um, a big movement in
LLMs was what we call the clawed code
moment. And in the sense that that was
the first use case where commercial
takeoff of these technologies happened
in robotics we think of the chat GPD
moment. I want to define this next one
after that the clot code moment when the
first commercial use case really takes
off just rockets off. And so your um
assessment, we'll start this time with
you way your assessment of what year
does the first true commercially viable
use case just takes off in the wild and
then if you have an idea for what that
use case is just a word or two on the
use case as well.
>> Wow that that's pretty challenging. I'll
just try my best to give the number. So
um my guess would be around three years.
So that so uh one thing is that we may
also want we may also expect the data
modality to uh to be somehow fulfilled
not just the for example a lot of
egocentric or third person view kind of
large scale data but also the uh
necessary physics modalities that can be
well grounded and associated with that.
So those kind of data accumulation would
take some time and that could be one of
the like gain for having such kind of
capability for the robotic foundation
model.
>> Perfect. Three years Sergey.
>> I promise I picked this number before
you answered but my answer is also three
years. I picked it in advance though.
[laughter] Uh so good good check. Uh but
I actually don't know the area. And I
think that the key here is to have
models that are sufficiently general to
radically lower the barrier to exploring
different applications so that the
community can collectively can get
through as many different possibilities
as possible to arrive at that solution.
So I think the key there is a general
model so we can explore lots of
applications.
>> That's a great point. Three years two
three years ma
>> I'm gonna say three years to not
>> oh come on no [laughter] okay I'll say
I'll say two. Um and I think the area is
going to be somewhere in an industrial
area because of a semiructured domain
possibly availability data
>> could be warehousing could be
manufacturing right so um I actually
think that the technology is sort of
there it's more of a question of finding
the right like economics
>> data data inputs and environments where
you can actually deploy which is where I
think for instance deploying large
robots in the home in terms of safety
issues is probably further out so I
think these semiructured environments
where you can sort of tailor the use
case, bring in general models, but also
combine them with like training onsite
or training in simulation. I think
that's going to be
>> great. Two years to the billion dollar
moment, Jim.
>> Earliest 2030 and we'll have more robots
than iPhones 2035 and we're going to
solve all robotics, everything, personal
robot, industrial robot, no later than
2040.
>> Amazing. Amazing. and ask us bring us
home. Are we going to go longer than
four or less than two? Those are the
bounds right now.
>> I think there's a wide uncertainty bar
when it comes to uh deploying robotics
in for household tasks. I think I agree
with Michael in terms of like for like
very narrow enterprise use cases uh in
like you know things like logistics or
um uh
in kind of the factory like you're
you're going to see deployment within
the next kind of you know two or three
years. Uh but when it comes to actually
dealing with the complexity of like a a
home and being able to operate
autonomously at like many nons of
reliability, it's going to I think
probably uh 5 to 10 years seems more
likely.
>> Can I can I give an upper bound? I think
for some economies and this is not a
technical argument, but we're going to
have to solve it in 10 years. So if you
take large Japanese corporations, for
instance, in manufacturing, any
industry, 60% of the workforce is 50
years or older. And so in 10 years they
will all be gone.
>> So those are the bounds. Two to 10.
Let's solve it by then.
>> All right. All of you are at the top of
your domain, top of your fields. I
really appreciate you spending your
Saturday afternoon with us. Thank you so
much for the wonderful presentations and
the chat.
[applause]
Hello. Um, thank you so much for our
amazing speakers for this amazing
session on robotics and work models.
We're now taking a 10 minutes break and
then uh right after the break we will
come back with a panel on agentic AI on
capital markets and then a fireside chat
between Andrew Andrew and Alfred Lane.
So now more than you're more than
welcome to stretch your legs, take a
bathroom break, walk around, and then be
back in 10 minutes. Thanks very much.
Now
heat.
Hello all. How's everyone? Was it a good
break?
>> Good break. Everybody caffeinated.
Ready for uh some amazing insights? I
hope so. We have a great group gathered
here today. My name is Brad Olsen. I'm
the deputy bureau chief at the Wall
Street Journal for technology and um I'd
love to actually allow these panelists
to introduce themselves. Uh and I've
asked each of them to think kind of have
a response ready for like what I call
like a starter question. I think one of
my favorite things to do when we talk to
people in AI or in the AI race is to ask
a little bit about what's a wow moment
they've experienced recently or even a
moment where they might have been
disappointed by the performance of an AI
model or whatever their expectations
were. And so I'd love to have everyone
introduce themselves and if you could
answer either side of that question when
you introduce yourself if you had a
recent wow moment or even uh some way in
which maybe what you thought would work
with AI didn't live up to expectations.
You want to start? Oh, sure. Sure. So,
hi everybody. I want to thank the
sponsors for inviting me. My name is
Jeff Wcker. I run engineering for an
investment management firm called Two
Sigma. Um before that I was a uh uh a a
partner in the first chief data officer
for Goldman Sachs and uh uh before that
I renovated I was at Bridgewater
Associates and renovated uh uh their
investment engine. I can keep going but
I'm an old guy so there's a lot of
before thats as well. So we'll uh we'll
stop there. Do uh do you want to do you
want my answer for your question?
>> I think I'd love to. It's a nice
conversation starter.
>> So, amazing things. I'm embarrassed to
say that a few years back I tried to use
one of the LLMs for parenting advice and
it was terrible. Just absolutely
terrible. Um,
and I've tried it more recently and I
actually got some pretty impressive
results. Um, uh, which I don't know if
the LLMs have gotten better or I got a
lot worse, but uh, but very impressive.
Anyway,
>> very cool.
Hi, I'm Jen Alam. I'm one of the
co-heads for one of the AI teams at
Deeshaw. Um, and something that I found
delightful recently, perhaps not revoly
in usage, is having AI be an executive
coach. I hope I'm not alone in this room
as being the only one with growth areas.
Um, but it's delightful if there's
something you're working on. Dehore is
very known for precise communication and
so it's an area I want to get better at
and it's both wonderful for timely
actionable insight qualitative and
quantitative as long as you give it the
right context. Um and I'm getting a ton
of value out of it. So I love that about
it at the moment.
>> Wonderful.
>> Okay, go next. My name is Alina Zaryi. I
run deep learn research team at
Saskuana. Before that I had my own uh
startup. It was actually deep learning
hedge fund as well. And before that I
was information theorist. Uh I mean I
guess it's so easy to be excited about
entire like you know evolution of AI
like you know machine learning AI and
then like agentic systems in the past
few years particularly last year. What I
want to take is actually disappointment.
Uh I mean a few weeks ago I was maybe
month ago I was trying to work on a
research problem. I asked one of these
frontier AI models to help me like think
about it and it came up with something
super exciting, super amazing. Uh came
up with about 30 different uh plausible
solution. Each of those idea if I wanted
it myself, it would probably take me
months if not quarters.
Then I realized actually the uh hardest
part didn't disappear. It just moved.
Now I found myself instead of just
trying to come up with idea to generate
idea I was trying to figure out which of
these ideas it gave me worth my time and
that's the reminder to me that I mean
all of these like you know bottlenecks
all of these challenges they don't just
disappear they just move.
Yeah, my name is Lee Dang. Uh I spent
about uh 18 years at Microsoft. Um and
then I joined um Citadel and now
currently with uh VIT investment. So
so before Microsoft I was academia. Uh
at that time I started doing neural
network right. Uh it just never work
right. And even the first uh 10 years uh
at Microsoft, I turned everything all my
machine learning tools into basian
network uh you know the generative model
you know but not that by neural network
but by you know the standard statistical
method and the result is just slow you
know I work on voice recognition and
translation spoken language processing
um and the wow moment for me it started
in 2010
when I first got opportunity to look at
uh a neural network uh actually was
inspired by Jeffrey Hinton later on he
got Nobel Prize um and the first two or
three experiment that we tried already
just shoot down the error rate by about
one third to one half and I immediately
say throughout all other tools just
embrace uh neuronet network deep neural
network we built very uh at that time up
to about 13 14 layers in as early as
2010. Uh I was reminiscent with uh
Jennifer earlier today at that time. You
know, most of the people at Microsoft
wouldn't believe that it's that was my
big wow point. And then the second wow
moment for me was when JP came out. I
the first time I was trying uh JPT about
how many three years ago I just thought
that something must go wrong. That's
exactly what many people said during my
speech recognition time at Microsoft.
They said, "Oh, you probably mix
training and test data." Right? Now, for
CHG GBT, we actually were able to use
that, you know, as the product. So,
nothing could be wrong, right? Because
it's real testing. Uh, and then it took
me I have to get back at that time. I
was already in uh Wall Street there. Uh,
I have to get my previous uh team member
who used to report to me. He actually at
the time was leading uh the uh reasoning
team at Google and he had to explain to
me that there are certain kind of
decoding technique that is different
than the traditional machine learning
and then that make me immediately
realize that wow that's real. Um but now
when a gentic AI come out there that was
small amount of W moment. Um it actually
not just you know do pattern you know
recognition pattern matching you know
the kind of traditional machine learning
task but it actually can do the
reasoning but also it can also kind of
put things together. It actually does
knowledge kind of management and that
part really wow me. Okay I stop right
here. I think we've all had that
experience where there are series of
those moments for all of us. Um, one of
the things that I wanted to ask because
I I imagine many of you are here today
to hear from, you know, people um in in
finance and Wall Street. I'm interested
in maybe what the differences might be.
You know, a lot of a lot of people might
be familiar with AI in the context of
software engineering and the
capabilities that are possible, you
know, to accelerate software
engineering. But I wonder um if if any
of you could address the adoption curve
within finance. What are what are
different things that are in
consideration, you know, as opposed to
in a technology institution or
organization? What are different kinds
of things that are being looked at or
that are important?
>> So I'm happy to start and then turn over
to my colleagues. Um,
so I uh we are mostly at two sigma a
technology firm that invests. Um, of the
1,800 employees that we have about just
under a thousand are in engineering,
another four or 500 are modeling and
then all the rest of the firm. Uh, the
rest do everything else. And and so uh
for most engineers, you give them a new
tool. Um, and it's hard to believe. you
think about Claude being available in
February of 25. Uh we started using it
within a few weeks and WebGA within a
month uh six weeks and and so engineers
you see different rates of adoption but
you you see engineers ready to take
another tool in the toolbox look at it
and say oh I know how to build with it
and start going. What's exciting to me
is the potential to have everybody at
the firm think of themselves as AI
first. Um, and there are different rates
of adoption. Um and it's becoming very
clear as we look at at various metrics
that those that adopt sooner faster are
clearly get becoming much more
productive by a lot of different
measures that you look at code branches
or uh work things they've written things
they publish uh and so our goal is to
try to figure out what is the right set
of tools what's the right partnership
for everyone at the firm to be AI first.
And while a lot of our focus uh at the
firm is on the investment pipeline, of
course, there's every single other
workflow at the firm that can uh lend
itself to that. We're seeing people now
that have no technical backgrounds uh
starting to use Claude in auto mode or
uh or one of our in-house workbenches in
auto mode. And it's really impressive to
see people experiment and I think as a
result the rate of innovation now is as
high as it's been in recent memory.
>> Fascinating.
>> I guess I can add something to that. I
mean the adoption is real. I mean in
quantitive finance SAS particularly all
engineers researchers are using like you
know AI tools. I mean as Jeff mentioned
there are like you know different rate
some people use it more some people use
it less. But I mean one thing that is
different in finance compared to a
software company is that the cost of
mistakes. So in a software company if
you AI model make a mistake I mean
hopefully you have unit test you're
going to figure it out. You're going to
fix it and you move on. In finance and
many other fields it can cost a lot. It
can cost money. It can be kind of even
like you know a lot of other uh
dangerous thing to the entire like you
know kind of like society in some cases.
So we need to be uh I mean we in general
like you know quantitative finance has
been early adopter of many many things
whether is like you know statistical
learning whether it's machine learning
different type of thing but when it
comes to agentic system I mean we have
we need to be careful and then like you
know I would say that trust is something
that needs to be gained like there are
some things that I definitely use AI all
the time for and there are some stuff
that I prefer like you know human be
part of it and then the other thing is
that I think trust needs to be regained
like you know model change, data change,
market change, market shift, everything
happens and then something that you were
trusting six months ago might not be
like trustable right now. So I think
it's like all about like you know the
mistake and then the trust the model.
Uh, Jen, maybe one thing I'd like to get
your insight on is how how do you
encourage teams to experiment with and
evaluate kind of new AI tools before
deciding what to scale?
>> I think an underappreciated
quality of firms like ours is that in
many ways they operate like innovation
businesses. There's a there's a
relentless need to be able to innovate
on what you do and that means the DNA is
there for experimentation and history is
there for experimentation.
Dshore is uh perhaps known as one of the
original kind of quant funds. Of course,
a AI is in the DNA and as a federated
business with multiple strategies, we're
able to to to unlock experiments across
the organization and allow for a bottoms
up finding of where the value is. So, we
we think about the rate of learning and
the rate of discovery we have. Let lots
of experiments run. Be maximalist in the
policy. Build and buy and everything in
between and then see what catches fire
and then think about where we scale that
and for who and how. So it's a
continuous process that is very much
part of the DNA and that this new advent
of AI is accelerating.
>> Leah, I'd love to know in your
organization, how are you balancing the
experimentation versus cost problem that
a lot of companies are facing right now?
Oh yeah, very much so. Um,
so
compared with the high-tech wall, the
quant wall um has a similar kind of
workflow, right? You extract features
that's what we call alpha and then you
have a model to do the forecast just
like you know prediction you know
pattern recognition and then you do uh
experimentation and evaluation uh we
call the back testing whereas in
high-tech world you call the validation
and then you go on testing in the
high-tech world now we call the um you
know paper trading or online trading now
the key issue here is that the signals
are extremely noisy. The input signal is
noisy. The output signal is even more
noisy. So one of the reasons I actually
decided to move from Microsoft to find
uh to the wall street is I try to
understand exactly I thought that the
problem is going to be unsupervised
because the signal is so noisy you might
as well just you know forget about uh
the signal and it turned out that it's a
mix. you know if you're purely using
unsupervised learning you're not going
to go anywhere and then you do have a
little bit of super uh you know
supervision but it's extremely noisy the
first time I look at the data finance
data you know that's after residualizing
all the returns I thought that I got a
wrong data right it you know it's just
random noise or random walk almost
everything there but it turned out that
the signal is right you want to extract
very tiny bit of signal from there so we
need to use a special kind of technique
especially in the experiment experiment
implementation and evaluation side. So
earlier on we heard uh Google deep mind
uh v uh oral vine he went through a
recursive uh you know a self-improvement
pipeline all these pipeline we went
through them all uh but we emphasize a
lot more on the evaluation side and then
because if evolation output is very very
noisy you don't even know what will be
the right signal to predict and then how
do you provide the right feedback in
order to improve further improve your
features etc. So we put a lot of effort
on that but so the key uh over the past
few years of the work uh on upon AI um
it's not as much as you know making the
model bigger you expect you know to have
emergent uh capability coming out just
like large language model we try quite a
bit but we don't know how far we are
going to do but I my hunch is that we
need to go much further away because of
the nature of the noisy input output
right so we actually gave up on that
part. And then the key focus would be to
uh to your point how to make the entire
system to form a right self loop in such
a way that you know actually aentic uh
method is really the key that minimize
you know all the human effort engineers
e alpha engineers e you know effort to
put them into in place um and that's the
kind of focus where you know we have put
out in my current work
>> but if I could just add something to the
uh point about cost because it's I think
it's going to play a very a growing role
going forward. If I think about
historically our business uh when it was
founded 26 years ago, most of our
modeling was fairly low dimensionality
statistical models and then sort of low
to mid uh machine learning models and we
moved from that to ensembles and we
started to train our own transformers.
Uh then you have the you know with GPT35
coming out you fi finally had the
ability to to use publicly available uh
models because the frontier firms gave
you such a head start in training uh
that reduce the cost of doing that. Um I
think what we're seeing now with the
advent of agent agent centric workflows
uh we are on the eve of the potent
potentially an explosive use of uh
compute demand that we have to be pretty
careful of because if I if we have you
know if I use the two sigma example we
have uh 1,800 employees today but if
behind those 1,800 employees there are
quarter of a million agents doing
operation all making their own compute
demand that we really have to think
about the implications return on
investment of that. Now, to be fair, um
when you're seeking alpha, you dig a lot
of dry wells. There's no doubt about it.
Um but but at some point, you have to
look at the maturity model of the
investments that you're making in
identifying alpha opportunities and then
think through whether or not you're
failing fast enough to protect against
the massive investment demand that you
have in compute. Interesting. Um I I
think maybe to switch gears there
because you mentioned the personnel. One
thing that is a great question for all
organizations is like how the AI age has
changed kind of the search for talent,
the recruiting process and would love to
hear from everyone about that and kind
of how different different things that
you look for has changed in this age and
in this era. Um obviously most people
are looking for people of talent, but
how do you how do you find them? How do
you sense that someone has a
experimentation capability and maybe the
skills to make a lot out of those
things?
>> I think yeah,
>> we think about um AI as an opportunity
creator, something that is helping us
innovate and drive higher quality work.
And so we are deep in finding great
talent continuously.
And Dehaw I think is known in some ways
for hiring particular types of people
and looks for curiosity, lifelong
learners, critical thinkers, systems
thinkers. These are qualities that are
becoming even more important now. And
when uh people commit to the firm and
have decadesl long careers as as is
common then actually you're looking for
a degree of adaptability that they will
have multiple careers within the
organization. And so as I'm building out
a team and I'm thinking about how to
hire, it's kind of emphasizing those
qualities more alongside functional
expertise and then building on that
thinking ahead to what's the next role
and the role after that that they'll be
doing um with us.
>> Yeah, I completely agree. And then I
think some of the qualities still is
going to stay the same. So we want smart
people like that who are curious who are
asking like right question who can work
independently and then like you know
these qualities matters actually maybe
more than before. One thing that changed
though is that uh like the interview
process the type of thing that we were
questioning people before was built for
a time that implementation was the
hardest part. Now that AI does good
amount of implementation for us, the
type of things that we care about change
as well. We need to make sure that
people can adapt to this kind of thing.
They can use the tools properly and they
can detect if like an AI system like you
know confidently wrong about something
they should be to detect it. One thing
I'm actually wondering is that the next
generation how they going to develop
judgment like if you think about
judgment traditionally what we were
doing is that we try something we make a
mistake we learn from that mistake and
then how judgment is being developed now
that AI does most of the experimentation
for us like you know the question is
that how that judgment is going to be
developed and this is the question I
guess for next generation.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So in my firm for example uh
like maybe maybe just two years ago
right most of the team members are you
know PhDs from you know Ivy League from
mathematics you know from physics you
know some computer science da nowadays I
think twothird of them are no longer
with the firm um before uh one one
sometime uh every now and then we get
the CV you know coming from
uh you know universities is uh they
don't even have PhD we don't even look
at the CV just say sorry we don't hire
you know non-P PhD but now we have maybe
more than half of the uh the people who
are not uh you know who are not even PhD
you know uh for the for the intern we
actually enjoy undergraduate student
senior undergraduate student to come
they actually can do agentic work
probably faster than you know full-time
the people there so So, so all the
talents actually profile changed quite a
bit just over two past two years.
>> Yeah, if I could just clear something
up, we are hiring. We are hiring and uh
what uh but I do think what people are
doing is very different. Um we've
eliminated coding tests of course um
because we'd be testing LLMs and not
people. So, so, so, uh, but I do think
that, uh, the kind of scientist, the
kind of computer scientist, the kind of
engineer is I is going to be even more
important to us going forward. The their
ability to take a problem, decompose
problems clearly into components. Can
they actually prompt to get the kinds of
outcomes that we really want to see? Can
they design agents that are able to use
judgment and and and really help to
accelerate either the generation of
features, the generation of models, the
generation of order placement or
portfolio construction models. The
that's going to be critical. And so
we're looking for people that have the
cognitive depth to uh be inquisitive and
learn our business and then bring to
bear the skills that they've learned in
their various scientific backgrounds to
apply them to deconstruct uh the ideas
that they may have about what's possible
in the future and then deliver outcomes.
Well,
>> I think it's certainly good for everyone
in this room to know that uh people are
hiring that it's possible out there. Um,
I think another thing that I'd like to
ask that I think is relevant to the
talent question for those of you who are
willing to answer is if you were going
to design a quant firm from scratch.
>> Yeah.
>> What might be different about it now?
You know, in this age, what might you do
differently than maybe the existing
systems and infrastructure that you've
seen?
>> So, I think uh one thing that I would do
is that I think quantitative trading has
two part. One is the research side, the
other one is trading. uh one side is
creating the knowledge, the other side
is using the knowledge. So like you know
if I want to build a like you know new
quantitative trading firms I basically
focus more and more on the research side
and there are a couple of things I'm
going to do on research side. The first
thing I'm going to do make sure that
every single experiment the failures the
successes everything that has been done
is become part of a knowledge of the
organization. I guess uh there are
things that I mean especially the
failures many people like you know put
them in their mind and then when they
leave the company the knowledge goes
with them. The second thing I would do
is that making sure that like you know
the evaluation become become part of the
research loop not something that we add
at the end and the third thing I'm going
to do essentially is going to be making
sure that uh researchers the human
research and AI researchers go to the
same kind of like you know research
process they're going to be this
evaluated the same way regardless of
whether like you know is AI generated or
like you know like you know human
generated and then the knowledge we're
going to learn from both of them is
going to go to the knowledge of the
entire like you know organization. I
look at research as like you know not a
collection of like you know task is a
like you know a process of continuous
learning and I think that's the like you
know big distinction
>> while we build a fair amount at Dshaw we
also partner widely with companies
outside and like to be a good partner in
terms of uh collaboration especially
when you think about kind of enterprise
readiness for what it takes to be able
to deliver a product in a regulated
space where we care about security and
care about our IP deeply. And when we
look at at products, I think to Ali's
point about the kind of knowhow the
organizations already have both
technically and knowledgewise, I think
there is an opportunity for even sharper
thinking about the value proposition of
new products in this space about what
they would be how they would be additive
to companies like these.
>> Well, I have a bit of a wildcard
question. I want to see if people are up
for answering, but I think I'd love to
hear what so many people think about
this question. If you're not up for
answering, we can go to another one, but
um I'd love to know if anyone wants to
weigh in. What is one widely held belief
about AI that you think is wrong?
I think the idea that you need fewer
people. Um certainly there are roles and
jobs that are not going to exist in the
future. But the idea that you don't need
technologists, scientists,
mathematicians
uh in in a a world where more systemic
decision support is going to be the
future I think will turn out to be
false. Now I believe what will happen as
a result is a whole host of new roles
are going to be generated to take up the
the changes that are going on in the
workforce. Um but I do I do believe that
one of the ideas that are being
advocated uh is uh that there won't be
opportunities for people in the future.
It just doesn't make a lot of sense. It
hasn't been true with any other major
invention over over human history. The
world's changed, the markets get grow,
and the opportunity for more people to
make an impact continues to grow.
>> Does anyone else want to try that one?
>> I guess I can. You go ahead. Go ahead.
>> Yeah. So, we heard earlier talk several
talk in robotics and also in um in
foundational model, right? People still
talk about, you know, one wave of
scaling and the second wave of scaling
that could be third wave scaling. So I
personally feel that maybe it could I
think for robotic could be true whereas
in finance I just don't believe uh this
is going to be correct. Uh we have we
have done a lot of work over the past
few years trying to scale. We never
reached the point where we have the
emerging uh sort of emerging capability
come up. But I think in finance the most
important part really is the systematic
way of looking at the full system right
especially the integration between
different part components of machine
learning especially at the output side
evaluation and the feedback because
feedback in the financial market is a
very very different
type of um you know problem than in the
high-tech
um And that part of design probably
carries a lot more weight in the
Atlantic area. Um, and I remember when I
moved from Microsoft to Citadel, uh,
seven years ago, um, you know, my big
boss, you know, very wealthy, uh, you
know, billionaire, right? He actually
first personally told me that
I we hire you. uh we know that you know
you disrupt the speech recognition you
practically solve a speech recognition
problem and then you do naturally we
hire you it's not we don't expect you to
bring that kind of expertise to sit
there because if you build a system for
translation system for recognition
system it may work today and then more
likely next week you don't have to adapt
right maybe you know maybe uh when you
uh wait for three or four years when you
have different president For example,
the language change right and then you
know you have one president different
policy different uh and then language
model change that will affect speech
recognition at that time you have to
adapt and maybe for voice um you know
you might want you have to wait maybe a
few years when coding standard changes
maybe whatever system that you train
before may not may break uh if you want
to bring that kind of system into
finance world you're going to fail
Because in financial uh market every
time you put order into the market
people react that differently it changes
the environment much more so than the
high-tech war. Um I think this is uh you
know the drastic different uh difference
between uh you know different world. So
I think a traditional way of thinking uh
in high-tech world of scaling and then
doing you know all sort of things that
you heard here maybe most of them may
not be applicable to us.
>> Well thank you all for joining and thank
you for hearing and listening to us. Um
I think that concludes our panel today
and uh yeah thanks everyone for
listening. Thank you.
>> [applause]
>> Thank you.
And uh it's it's my pleasure now to just
introduce the the next speakers. Um uh
we'll be hearing um there's a fireside
chat and we'll be able to hear from
Andrew. Um the co-founder of Google
Brain and uh um anyway, it's silly for
me to introduce these people. They have
so many titles, but um he's a co-founder
of Corsera.
uh he actually coined the term agentic
relative to aentic AI. So that's pretty
interesting. And um also is a founder of
deep learning AI. And then also he'll be
speaking to Alfred Lynn uh the general
partner at Sequoia Capital. Thank you.
[applause]
Andrew, I think you and I are the last
ones, so uh we better be entertaining.
>> Counting on you for that. [laughter]
>> All right, we'll start with uh
heavyhitting questions. You said in
February that AGI is about 50 years
away.
>> Oh, I see.
>> You still believe that given how fast
things are moving?
I think depending on how you define AGI,
we might have gotten to AGI either 30
years ago or I think quite possibly not
yet for many decades. The definition I
know is AI that could do any
intellectual task a human can. And that
means AI that could take five years and
write a novel PhD thesis or maybe faster
or AI that any of us with a few hours of
practice could learn to drive a truck
through a forest. So AGI seems to me
like would have to do that too. But
because of um incentives between you
know a Microsoft and a open AI contract
which has changed so that's gone away.
There was a specific financial incentive
to lower the bar for AGI to make it
easier to get there. And there was this
definition of um AI that could do you
know 50% of all economically useful
work. But if only we had put in place
that definition a 100 years ago then as
most of the work transition from
agriculture to non-aggricultural work
then I would declare we got to AGI like
30 years ago or 50 years ago or
something. So depending on how you
define it I think the original
definition is still many decades away
but I think because the agreement
between um Microsoft and OpenAI you know
I I think that uh there's now less hype
uh about AI which I think is a good
thing. All right, another hard-hitting
question. Um, a lot of controversy about
open models.
Uh, a lot of talk in Silicon Valley, a
lot of talk in Washington,
a lot of people posting about open
models. In fact, Jensen's first tweet,
he's never sent out an expost ever
before. His first expost was about open
models. Um,
and defending it. What do you think of
open models?
Why do you think we need it? What's the
concerns around security? Are those
things valid?
>> You know, over the last three years,
two, three years ago, I was surprised at
the intensity of the attack on open
weight models. I think many of you
already seen, right? If someone's spent
billions of dollars training a model,
it's kind of inconvenient as someone
else releases an openweight version that
degrades the value of that investment.
So kind of two three years ago I was in
the room when a number of executives
from a number of companies kind of the
obvious ones were saying to government
regulators frankly misleading hyperbole
things about AI safety um in order to
try to drive recapture. I think I'm
actually very glad that a little bit
later because of the work that a lot of
the open source community did flying to
DC, speaking with Congress, speaking of
the White House that at this moment in
time there's broad awareness in
Washington DC about the regry capture
moves. Um, and I think but but at the
same time I was actually really happy
that Jensen put out that statement
really well written worth reading if you
not yet read you know the his statement
on why open weight models are important
thing. Um, and right now my readers, the
battle for the sentiment of open way
models is won on social media, but it is
not yet won in Washington DC and in our
state houses. So, we cannot yet relent
on our defense on openweight models.
From what I'm seeing, I think um open
models seem safer to me than closede
models. In fact, just last week I had my
own um example of the uh OpenAI hacking
hugging face and hugging face needing
open way model to defend hugging face.
So my team was doing um security review
of open source agent harness that my
friend Rohit Prasad and I had released
called open worker and both fable 5 and
um uh 5.6 soul refused you know beyond a
certain point and we actually used GM
5.2 too in Q3 in order to complete our
own security review. To be clear, um I
hope Anthropic and OPI succeed. I like
both companies. I I I might be the only
person in the world that both Sam and
Dario has worked for. So I really hope
these businesses succeed.
[laughter] At the same time, I hope we
find a path to all of my friends in
these companies doing well and also
having a wonderful fantastic open way
open source ecosystem because that
ensures that there are no I don't want
there to be gatekeepers to AI.
Yeah, thank you. [applause]
I couldn't I couldn't agree more. And
also since everything costs so much, why
pay for more to open AI and anthropic if
you can actually train something
yourself, you're going to do that for
certain things because you need the
latest intelligence and you're going to
want certain other things to be trained
yourself. So
>> and and remember I think Squire actually
came out in favor of open source and
you're actually ahead of many other VCs.
I really respected that. I I think the
you know the history of the history of
venture capital is to try to find things
that are cheaper and open source is a
form open source let's like move all the
way back to open source and not open
weight because I think it is it's
clarifying to study business history a
lot of the products that were developed
on the internet were built on open
source and if the the open-source
software was not available a lot of
things would cost a lot more and take a
lot longer to
and only certain companies would be able
to sort of build that type of
infrastructure. Um and uh open source is
the reason why uh there's so much
diversity of databases, so much
diversity of browsers, so many diversity
of many many things that we do. And open
source for a startup for software was a
form of distribution. And it was a cheap
way to show how smart you are, how
capable you are, how you're able to
build something and give it to the world
to use and then let other developers
develop with you. Um, it was a form of
recruiting. These things were controlled
by large companies for a period of time.
And so I think open weight models have a
place, closed models have a place, open
models have a have a place. And the
knock on open has always been it's not
as safe. That was true with security
with security for software open source
software as well. Yes, you have to patch
those uh holes if you're going to use
them, but it is a very fast way for you
to get up and running. Um,
some other sort of hard-hitting
questions.
You said recently that there's bubble
risk in the model layer.
>> Bubble risk in the model layer.
>> Asking I'm I'm asking for a friend, you
know, in the investment community.
Should we be worried?
>> Yeah. Now, I I think the other side I
don't know Alfred likes doing this
hard-hitting stuff. I don't know why. I
I think the part of the statement I was
more confident in was um demand for
inference. I think there's no practical
ceiling and so as much capital going
into building data centers, you know, if
we build the data centers, we will use
up I think all the inference capacity we
can build for for quite some time. Um
doesn't mean no one will lose money. You
know, maybe we'll overbuild, but that
risk seems lower. And um the model layer
you know has been the the the kind of uh
intelligence per dollar invested is a
tough equation right the capital going
in is growing you know very quickly the
intelligence is maybe also growing very
quickly so where that plays out I think
I don't know I'm cautiously optimistic
there isn't a bubble but I think it's I
I wish I could rule it out uh but I'm
actually less worried about um I think a
lot we we clearly need a lot more data
into buildouts for inference because
even take AI agent coding I think
penetration is very low but all of us
that use AI coding agents see so much
you know speed and efficiency gain so
I'm very confident that AI coding just
as one example will have vastly greater
penetration in the future and drive
vastly greater demand for tokens than
there is now
>> so we're at the agent AI summit so what
do you what kind of agents are you
building we coding agents is
What's as what's potentially as big as a
coding agent in the future?
>> I don't know. I uh I wish I knew. Yeah,
maybe I share one perspective. One thing
I think a lot about is um uh so it turns
out that where AI is creating value
with the rise of internet there was the
horizontal information search layer
where you know Google maybe Bing won
that and then there are a lot of
verticals right with rise. So kind of um
Uber and lift fought out for ride
sharing, travel velocity, expedia, you
know, for out of travel does retail and
so on. I think what's happened is for
the horizontal information discovery
layer, um track GP and Gemini seem to
have the leading position pretty hard to
displace and then for the vertical
applications, the bucket that's the
single most valuable so far seems to be
AI coding where coding agents have have
kind of been incredible. Um I feel like
my team uses a lot of coding agents for
uh data science work as well. Um I spend
a lot of time spend some time the
financial sector. Uh so we do some work
with some large banks. Um and I find
there are a lot of agent workflows that
useful for financial services as well.
But um it feels like there are I don't
know I wish I knew I I I know Alfred
actually spent a lot of time thinking
about what are the new categories that
may emerge right not just what we could
do a bit better but the brand new
creations you say the
>> yeah if I knew I would start a company
it's a great it's maybe the best time
ever to start a company I um we often
talk about uh at Sequoia that in
technology there's accelerating change
and there's two parts to accelerate
change that is very difficult. One of
which is what we're talking about today,
we didn't talk about three months ago.
Which means that in three months,
whatever we're talking about today,
we're not talking we won't be talking
about in the future. And if you're
you're building a company, which is even
more important than if you're like me
who's investing in people who are
building a company, you really need to
be able to build something that lasts
over a longer period of time. uh if a
comp today given the amount of capital
that is needed to with compute you're
going to be raising a substantial amount
of money uh and you you want it to last
for a decade um it's very very hard to
sort of understand what's going to last
for a decade but I can tell you that um
one of the things that I think people
often like confuse is like the immediate
thing that seems obvious obvious
uh those things are going to get done by
even large e even you know some of you
in the audience but it's al also going
to be done by large companies and I use
like the analogy of mobile everything
that was on the internet made it to
mobile like mobile apps were a little
bit complicated but it wasn't that hard
to take mobile to take the internet and
make it mobile web or mobile app and
then I look at this device what is a
from the last device that you had which
is a laptop. This thing is always on. So
for communications all the apps around
communications blew up you know even
email blew up or texting blew up but you
have to find something unique and
non-obvious. So even though there are
lots of messaging services WhatsApp was
different because it was about long
distance SMS which is solving a cost
problem. uh SMS inside the this country
we all pay one data plan it wasn't that
big of a deal but if you're sending
international SMS that's very very
expensive so international SMS WhatsApp
solved that and that became a big
company and this device had two things
that your laptop doesn't have one of
which is the camera so everybody became
a photojournalist so you can invest in
that area and the other thing was GPS
everybody be had GPS on their phone at
some point and that was not true from
the previous generation and so often
when I hear about companies that are
taking existing context and processes
and feeding it into AI like that's
obviously going to get done but the sort
of what is uniquely going to be made
differently uh in AI I think we haven't
pushed the boundaries of that and I'm
looking for that
yeah I share Another thing you know I
think that um a lot of people think
about what are the new modes in software
and I think it's actually a very valid
question um and I find that the lot of
stuff that can be built and if it's
valuable let's actually build it but if
whatever you build can be replicated by
anyone with a coding agent in three
months then the traditional way of
running SAS businesses where you know
you build software and sell similar
software for a long time seems like that
might have to change um so I think that
the analysis of most of what are the
deep tech things that are genuinely hard
to replicate and that are going to be
valuable for a long term. And also um
I'm actually seeing some businesses
where frankly the frontier labs have
done this. You build stuff that goes
obsolete in three to six months but you
keep on having new stuff that keeps on
getting obsolete but you accumulate some
asset along the way. So keep on building
something that keeps on going obsolete,
but everything that quickly goes
obsolete helps you accumulate some asset
before it goes obsolete. So the asset
you end up accumulating over time grows
into hopefully a more defenseful mode.
So I think these new patterns of
building businesses um you know are
quite quite interesting.
Uh
when we talked about the bubble thing uh
jobs AI jobs no job no AI job copyps
you've said that a few times. Yes
>> I agree with you. So what why do you
think that?
>> Yeah. So this idea that AI will put 50%
of people out of a job there'll be
rioting in the streets or whatever this
is false. There will be no AI job
apocalypse. Um, part of the regulatory
capture fear narratives of businesses
was this, you know, my technology is
dangerous. No, mine is even more
dangerous. No, regulate me harder. It
it's just kind of um and I think uh what
I I feel like Wall Street Journal just
reported a few days ago that even some
large businesses that thought AI would
reduce labor um is actually turning
around and starting to hire more. And if
you look at the job most affected by AI,
it is actually software engineering
because of coding agents. So much
service automation. The software
engineering job market is very healthy
and frankly we just can't find enough
skilled AI engineers. I believe that as
AI in uh starts to enter other sectors
as well be it finance, marketing, you
know, HR,
administrative jobs and so on that we'll
see a similar pattern of um very rarely
job collapse but people actually end up
being busier. And what we've seen in
software engineering is if you take say
a back-end developer and they start
using a coding agent then it frees up I
don't know some of their time I don't
know 30 40 50% I'm not sure but that
remaining work that they do which is a
complement of the coding therefore
becomes even more valuable and if we
free up some of their time then say
front end or backend developers end up
rising and taking on a broader scope
which is why these days I don't hire are
front end or back end or whatever
developers. Almost all of my agents are
full stack developers because we can now
all do that. I'm seeing early signs of
this in other job roles as well where
previously maybe you had a marketing
coordinator that did one row you know
driving the coordition marketing
campaigns but if AI frees up 30 40% of
the time that marketing coordinator can
rise up and become more of a full cycle
marketer and run marketing campaigns
from start to finish do the data
analysis drive growth and so I think
this pattern will repeat in other
industries in other job categories as
well and the number of jobs where AI
could do 100% % of the time 100% of the
task that's causing a collapse of that
job category will be very small. What
this means is one of the challenges
ahead of us is when someone comes and
does oh one one thing I think all of us
use AI co agents a lot in this room
maybe I don't feel any more you know I
feel like I'm even busier than I ever
was right because when AI does some of
our job the compliment becomes even more
valuable but the challenge for a lot of
job roles will be upskilling uh so that
if 30% of your job goes away how do you
rise up and do that broader set of tasks
and also learn to use AI AI uh and so
that's why I think I also still spend a
lot of time at um Corsera and uh uh
Udemy and deep learning.ai and learn
vector which you just announced this
week to try to address that uh training
upskilling.
Yeah, I just I I fully agree with you
Andrew and I think the one thing that
people misunderstand we sit in an
academic institution here in academic
institution you solve one problem and it
creates every problem has a solution
that's part of the sort of thesis in in
academia and every solution creates more
problems and I don't think we're going
to run out of problems and there's maybe
the exact thing that you're doing today
is going to get autom automated. But you
know, if we lived 200 years ago, 80% of
us would be working on our farm to make
sure that we can feed ourselves. It's
kind of good that that we can automate a
lot of that so that we can do other
things. And so I fully agree that maybe
we won't as software engineer will not
be coding, but as the last panel said,
your ability to break down problems,
large problems into smaller and smaller
problems will become is is still going
to be important. your ability to figure
out which problems to solve is still
going to be important and those are
those are not going away.
>> Yeah. In fact, in terms of what's not
going away, I think um you know
sometimes people say [clears throat] I
feel like the job populace messaging has
made a lot of people nervous about jobs
unnecessarily.
Um and I feel like
uh it turns out in our surveys of excuse
me a lot of software professionals
there's a people are actually confused
about where to go and what to learn and
worried about learning something that
would go obsolete in three months. Um so
um spent a lot of my time thinking
through what is it what exactly are the
skills that being skilled at AI
engineering or being skilled at these
other things uh will what what that
would require and help people to get
there and and that feels important. I
know here in Silicon Valley there's a
ton of work on accelerating AI
development. Fully support that. Let's
keep working on that. I think the
complement of that has had insufficient
attention which is why I would like to
also spend more time on accelerating not
just AI development but on accelerating
human development. So that too seems
important to me.
>> So maybe following up on that you were
you're a PhD student here 20 years ago.
Is that right? Approximately
>> boy was that long? Yeah.
>> At [laughter] all that you've you've had
a fabulous career after graduating.
You're a researcher. You're academic,
you're a builder, you're a founder,
you're an investor. Uh you were at the
forefront of AI while you were at Google
Brain. What would you advise people in
the audience to do um in this kind of
day and age?
>> I think of all my credentials, you left
one out that I'm probably most proud of,
which is father. That that's really
precious.
>> Father is actually pretty fun, too. Yes.
[applause]
Thank you.
Um
this is the this sounds cliche but this
sounds like the best time ever to build.
Um
I find that my teams we see so many
opportunities and yes we can code faster
now because of coding agents but somehow
all of our
uh our appetite our list of ideas seems
to grow even faster than we can deploy
coding agents to to to to keep up with
us. Um, one thing that I found
interesting was for a long time my team
in addition to, you know, hiring people
with strong technical skills, strong AI
skills and all that, we tend to look for
people with a high degree of agency. um
meaning people that you know don't wait
to be told what to do but uh will look
around see what's going on in your
company or in your context or in your
academic university or whatever and have
high agency to just decide I'm going to
do this you know do it in a safe and
responsible way don't harm others but
really don't ask if there's some things
you don't need permission to do uh so
you don't harm others just go do it and
prove it out or go do it and if it fails
in a way that doesn't harm anyone that's
fine too. The thing that I found really
interesting was um we're actually seeing
in more and more job descriptions
companies looking for people with a high
sense of agency. Oh, and the weird way
of saying this is uh I see companies
looking for people that are highly
agentic.
[laughter]
>> How do you how do you screen for someone
who's highly has high agency or highly
agentic?
>> Um I think one of the ways to do is
actually behavioral interviewing. will
ask people what they're doing and if
someone says well the last five years I
did what my boss told me that's one type
of person but then there are people that
say you know what in my spare time I did
this on the weekend I did this and this
failed this failed oh but that thing
worked and I tried this I tried this it
didn't work but that worked there are a
lot of people that that frankly oh
[laughter] I think it's also so much fun
so I don't know last night um I was
running uh codeex and uh clock code in
parallel with the same prompt to wake up
this morning to see which one did better
and then actually in the car ride over
here, you know, I started another. Okay,
it's just I I I do this stuff because
it's fun, right? And and I think uh
sometimes I build something that ends up
being useful to other people too and
that's very satisfying and a lot of time
I build stuff that to totally useless
and they will never see the light of
day. But that also, you know, the the
many very inexpensive failures is also a
really fun thing to do. someone could do
it in a responsible way that doesn't
risk you know anyone.
>> Well, that's all the questions I have.
Thank you very much, Andrew. I
appreciate it.
>> Thanks, A. [applause]
Thank you so much. This ends the uh the
program for today and then we have a
poster presentations and uh reception
food outside on the Loros Plaza. So uh
enjoy. Thank you so much. We'll see you
tomorrow back in the stage.